<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short view of the principal duties of the Christian religion with plain arguments to perswade to the sincere and speedy practice of them : to which is added, a prayer suited to the whole, to be used morning and evening / by a divine of the Church of England for the use of his parishioners.</title>
            <author>Wrench, Jonathan, 1667?-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3679A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875886</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152530</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96969)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152530)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2300:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short view of the principal duties of the Christian religion with plain arguments to perswade to the sincere and speedy practice of them : to which is added, a prayer suited to the whole, to be used morning and evening / by a divine of the Church of England for the use of his parishioners.</title>
                  <author>Wrench, Jonathan, 1667?-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Knapton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Price 3 d. or 20 s. per Hundred."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Anglican authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152530:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>SHORT VIEW</hi> OF THE PRINCIPAL DUTIES OF THE Chriſtian Religion. WITH Plain Arguments to perſwade to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and ſpeedy Practice of Them.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A Prayer ſuited to the Whole, to be uſed <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>For the Grace of God that bringeth Salvation has appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all Men; teaching us, that denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent World; looking for that bleſſed Hope and the glorious Appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 
               <bibl>Tit. 2. 11, 12, 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By a Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the Uſe of his Pariſhioners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>I. Knapton,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church. Yard. 1700.</p>
            <p>Price 3 <hi>d.</hi> or 20 <hi>s. per</hi> Hundred.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152530:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152530:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my beloved Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners of <hi>Ailes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>AS my hearts Deſire and Prayer to God for you is, that ye may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 1</note> So it ſhall be my great Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to guide and aſſiſt you, in this important Buſineſs of <hi>working out your own Salvation.</hi> And in order thereto I <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 12</note> have in the following Pages given you (as it were in one View) a Summary of all thoſe <hi>Chriſtian Duties</hi> (with their Motives to them) which I conceive ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> which (being ſuch) I intend (God willing) to make the conſtant Subject of my publick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes among you. And therefore I do earneſtly recommend them before-hand to your ſerious and conſtant Peruſal, that ſo your Minds, by forming the ſame Notions of the <hi>Chriſtian Doctrin</hi> with my ſelf, may better apprehend my Meaning in my Sermons, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be the better enabled, not only
<pb facs="tcp:152530:3"/> 
               <hi>to keep in memory what is preached unto you,</hi> but alſo to edifie or profit by it.</p>
            <p>And the great concern I have for your Eternal Welfare, makes me the more deſirous of your ready complyance with theſe my Endeavours, to <hi>build you up in your moſt holy Faith;</hi> the end whereof is nothing leſs than <hi>the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Souls.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved and remembred, that our compoſition is not made up of what is ſenſible only (though we chiefly converſe with this) but that Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of a Soul, as well as a Body, and our experience may convince us, that the World is not a ſuitable, or ſatisfact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 15.</note> good for the one, though it be for the other; which plainly ſhews that our chief End is, not to eat, and drink, and ſleep, and carry on a few wordly Deſigns; &amp; then go out of the World as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, &amp; leſs innocent than we came into it; but our great End is, to cultivate our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Part, and by the conſtant exerciſe of <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Religion</hi> fit our Souls for that <hi>ſpiritual and immortal Life,</hi> the loſs whereof, not even the whole World it ſelf, can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate; <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 26.</note> and yet nothing can put us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Poſſeſſion of it, but <hi>keeping the Commandments.</hi> For ſo it has pleaſed <note place="margin">—19. 17.</note> the Wiſdom of God to make Religion, or Obedience to his Laws, at once the Condition of our future Happineſs, and
<pb facs="tcp:152530:3"/> the neceſſary Preparation for it. For 'tis our likeneſs to, or reſemblance of God, that muſt diſpoſe us to reliſh any Pleaſure in the preſence and enjoyment of him, (for no one delighteth in the converſation of him, who is of a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er contrary to his own) and 'tis our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Will, that muſt make us like him, (i. e.) <hi>holy as he is holy,</hi> and <note place="margin">1 Pet 1. 15, 16.</note> conſequently happy as he is happy.</p>
            <p>So that the various Duties of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, laid before you in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Pages, are the very life of your Souls; and your Right or Claim to the one encreaſeth or diminiſheth, in the ſame Proportion, with your Practice of the other. And therefore as ye love your Souls ye muſt love your Duty; <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 16 Pſal. 119. 52.—165. 2 Cor. 112. Prov. 14. 32.</note> for there is nothing elſe can afford you any ſolid Comfort in this World, or any reaſonable hopes of Happineſs in the other.</p>
            <p>And it may be of great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your Duty to conſider, that as it is thus exceeding neceſſary to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; So it is with all as eaſie to be known. It is made ſo plain, that <hi>he who runs may read it,</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſeems to have been more throughly underſtood, (I am ſure much better practiſed) by poor <hi>Sheperds,</hi> and ignorant <hi>Fiſhermen,</hi> than by the moſt learned <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>Diſputers of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:152530:4"/> 
               <hi>this World;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> though a <note place="margin">Acts 22. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Scholar,</hi> was yet to preach the Goſpel, <hi>not with Wiſdom of Words;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 17.</note> there is not ſo much need of Logick or the Art of reaſoning, as of <hi>true Faith and Piety</hi> to underſtand it. So that if ye bring but along with you to theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers an <hi>honeſt and docible temper of Soul,</hi> I could hope ye might (with as little <note place="margin">James 1. 21</note> trouble as ye could deſire) know enough <hi>to make you wiſe unto Salvation.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 3. 15</note>
            </p>
            <p>And when once ye have attained to ſuch a degree of Knowledge in theſe neceſſary Duties, then all that remains to be further urged, is only that ye would pleaſe to remember our Saviour's Words to his Diſciples; <hi>If ye know theſe things, happy are ye if ye do them,</hi> and that <note place="margin">John 13. 17.</note> ye may, as 'tis the earneſt deſire: So it ſhall be the great Endeavour of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt faithful Friend and loving Paſtor, Jonathan Wrench.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152530:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſhort View of the Principal Duties of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>GOD, <hi>Who would have all men to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and come to the Knowledge of the Truth,</hi> has implanted in every Man a Deſire of Happineſs; and in the Goſpel has made true Religion, that is to ſay, <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2. Matthew 7. 21. Heb. 12. 14.</note> a faithful Obſervance of the Laws of Chriſt, neceſſary for the Attainment of that Deſire. So that it becomes at once every Man's Duty and Intereſt to acquaint himſelf with this true Religion, as being the one thing needful for the Object of his Thoughts, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his Practice.</p>
            <p>And as 'tis your Duty thus to learn: So (having the Care of your Souls upon me) I think it mine to inform you; <hi>what ye muſt do to inherit eternal Life,</hi> and that is, in ſhort, what the Doctrin of the Goſpel, or (as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it, what <hi>the Grace of God which (brings Salvation, and has appeared to all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Men) teacheth us,</hi> namely, <hi>that Denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and wordly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent World.</hi> This is the Sum of what we, on our Part, promiſed to God and Chriſt to perform, when we were baptized into the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> for Baptiſm is that Ceremony, by which God enters into Covenant with the Perſons to be baptized, wherein God is pleaſed to promiſe certain Advantages to them on his Part, and the Perſons to be baptized engage to obſerve certain Conditions on theirs. The Terms of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152530:5"/> Stipulation, or the Covenant to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Gods part, are (as our Church Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm informs us)</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we ſhall be made Members of Chriſt, (that is to ſay) Members of his <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Body, the Church,</hi> whereof Chriſt himſelf is <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 5.</note> the Head, from whom, we are to expect all our Strength and Power to <hi>live as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> or as Chriſtians, that <hi>walk</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>worthy of the Lord unto all Well-pleaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That we ſhall be made the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of God, that is, God (with whom we are in Covenant) will adopt us for his Sons <note place="margin">John 1. 12. Rom. 8. 15. Gal. 4. 5. 6. Luke 11. 13.</note> through Faith in, and Obedience to, Chriſt our Saviour, and as his Sons will expect only a filial Obedience; will readily paſs by our Infirmities, freely forgive our Sins, and be heartily reconciled to us, <hi>in and through the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> will beſtow upon us his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and with Him, a Supply of all things neceſſary for the Support of our ſpiritual Life and Growth in Grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as a Conſequence of this, we ſhall be alſo made Inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven; for if we are (as I ſaid juſt now we were) hereby <hi>made the Children of God,</hi> the <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 16, 17. Tit. 3. 5. 7. Heb. 1. 14.</note> Apoſtle's Concluſion is very ſtrong, <hi>that if Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, then Heirs, Heirs of God, and joynt Heirs with Chriſt,</hi> which can import nothing leſs than that we ſhall be, together with him, <hi>Heirs of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is, in ſhort, what God makes over to us in the Covenant of Baptiſm. All which we can expect, only upon Condition of the Performance of our Part of this ſacred Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. For ſuch is the Nature of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, that when one of the Perſons cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting or contracting receedeth from his Part of the Covenant he does thereby actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally acquit the other, with whom he cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted, from all Obligation to perform his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152530:5"/> Part of the Covenant. So that if we do not perform our Part of this Covenant, made in our Baptiſm, we thereby diſcharge God from the Obligation of performing his Part, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore it ſtands us in great ſtead to be very punctual in our Obſervance of thoſe Sacred Obligations, which we laid upon our Selves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n our Baptiſm, becauſe all the Priviledges belonging to us, as Chriſtians, together with our Eternal Life and Happineſs, either ſtand or fall by our well or non-Performance of them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or though <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and he only, <hi>has delivered us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1. 10. 2 Cor. 5. 18. Acts 4. 12. Heb. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>from the Wrath to come, and reconciled us to God by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Death;</hi> yet it muſt be with all remember'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the Benefits of his Death and Paſſion are all conditional, and that he is <hi>Become the Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f eternal Salvation, only to them that obey him.</hi> This being therefore a Matter of great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, I ſhall be the more particular (as far as my intended Brevity will admit) in my Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thoſe Conditions, which every Chriſtian is ſuppoſed to promiſe, in his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, faithfully to obſerve; and theſe are no more than what the <hi>Grace of God, (which has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men) teacheth us,</hi> viz. <hi>that denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12. Eccleſ. 12. 13. Phil. 2. 12. Pſal. 34. 14. 1 Pet. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and wordly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, Righteouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World;</hi> for <hi>This is the Whole of Man,</hi> the Sum of all that God requires at our hands; in order to the <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out our own Salvation,</hi> our Duty conſiſts only in theſe two Things, <hi>the Eſchewing Evil, and doing Good:</hi> The Evil to be eſchewed, denyed, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by us is comprehended under theſe few Words; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and wordly Luſts,</hi> and the Good, in theſe, <hi>The Living Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. One Condition of the forementioned Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges is, that we Deny <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs</hi> or Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. Now as <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Piety is that Part of our Duty, which has a more immediate Relation to God: So <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Impiety</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs</hi> may be ſuppoſed to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152530:6"/> comprehend in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all thoſe Sins, which are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled more immediately againſt Him, which may be all reduced to theſe two general Heads; Either,</p>
            <p>1. The Diſowning Him the true God, for our God; or</p>
            <p>2dly. The ſetting up other Gods beſides him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For,</p>
            <p>1. The Diſowning the true God for our <note place="margin">Joſh 24. 27. Pſal. 53. 9. Acts 17. 29. Pſal. 73. 9, 11. Matt. 5. 34. James 5. 12. Job 31. 26, 27, 28. Lev. 24. 15, 16. 1 Tim. 6. 1. 2 Tim. 3. 8. Tit. 1. 16.</note> God implies in it the Diſowning or Denying Him in our Thoughts; either thinking Him not at all, or thinking unworthily of him; the Denying Him in our Words, by arguing againſt his Being, and endeavouring to diſpute Him out of it: Swearing <hi>falſely or vainly</hi> by his Name, Curſing, Blaſpheming Him, and Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culing his ſacred Word. Laſtly, the Denying him in our Actions, <hi>Living as without God in the World,</hi> either by Omitting our known Duties to him, or Committing wilful Sins againſt him. All which are notorious Inſtances of Ungodlineſs.</p>
            <p>2dly. Ungodlineſs conſiſteth, not only in diſowning the true God any of the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd Ways, but alſo in Setting up other Gods beſides Him. Which I conceive, may be done either of theſe three Ways:</p>
            <p>1. By Subſtituting or Placing any other God in <note place="margin">Lev. 26. 1. Rom. 1. 23. Acts 17. 29. 2 Kings 17. 33. Zeph. 1. 5.</note> Room of the true God; or</p>
            <p>2dly. By worſhiping any other God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Him; or</p>
            <p>3dly. By giving thoſe Acts of Worſhip to any created Good, which are due to God alone.</p>
            <p>The two former of theſe relate to the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Worſhip of the Heathens, which was one great Sin, that Chriſtians formerly promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their Baptiſm to forſake, when they engaged to Renounce the Devil, and all his Works; and the latter is what Chriſtians, not only were, but are now a-days obliged to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, and yet but too frequently adhere to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152530:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; in that they are apt to Repoſe (as ſad Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience ſhews) a greater Reliance on their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordly Goods, fixing more Hope in them, and <note place="margin">Rom 25. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffording a larger ſhare of Love to them, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God himſelf; ſo making them their God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd their Happineſs. And accordingly we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old in Scripture of ſome, <hi>Whoſe God is their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elly;</hi> of others, <hi>Who ſacrifice to their Net, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 19. Hab. 1. 16. Pſal. 20. 7. Job 31. 24.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rn Incenſe to their Drag;</hi> of ſome, <hi>Who truſt in Chariots, and ſome in Horſes;</hi> of others, <hi>Who make Gold their Hope, and ſay to the fine Gold, Thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r Confidence;</hi> whoſe Sin is therefore juſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed * <hi>Idolatry;</hi> becauſe they affix thoſe Acts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Soul to a created Good, which ought to be employed upon God alone. So that all theſe wicked Practices, being in effect Idolatrous, may be juſtly ſtiled ungodly Actions, and are therefore included in this great Sin of Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which we muſt deny.</p>
            <p>2dly. Another Condition of the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Priviledges is, our forſaking wordly Luſts. By wordly Luſts I underſtand all the diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Motions, whether of our Underſtandings, Wills, Affections, or Appetites, as they are all depraved or corrupted by the Abuſe of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>1. As to the Diſorders of our Underſtandings when theſe, in Perſuance of their natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Knowledge, either thirſt after that which is neither proper, nor ſafe to be known, <note place="margin">Deut. 29. 29</note> 
               <hi>as the ſecret Things of God, and the pleaſures of Sin;</hi> or after that which is both ſafe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be known, in an undue manner, as when we immoderately ſtudy humane Learning to <note place="margin">Rom. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 3. 11.</note> the utter Neglect of divine Knowledge, and the Care of our Souls, our Underſtandings are in both theſe caſes productive of ſinful Luſts.</p>
            <p>2dly. There is a Corruption reſiding alſo in our Wills, which diverts them from their Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7</note> of chiefeſt good, as <hi>the Spiritual things of God,</hi> to their over-earneſt Perſuit of ſenſual Pleaſures,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152530:7"/> by which they being enſlaved and <hi>brought into Captivity to the Law of Sin,</hi> are likewiſe product<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 23.</note> of many ſinful Luſts. But,</p>
            <p>3dly. And above all, our Affections have ſuffer'd very much by the Abuſe of our ſelves, are very extravagant in their Motions, and <note place="margin">Col. 1. 21.</note> withal but too eaſie to be miſled; thus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more common, than to ſee the two great governing Paſſions in us, I mean our Love and Hatred, miſplaced, by loving what we ought to hate, ſuch are ſinful Pleaſures; and hating that, which we ought to love, ſuch <note place="margin">Pſal. 97. 10</note> are God and Goodneſs; or if we love and hate what we ought, yet it is often done in a <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 37.</note> diſproportionate manner, either by perſuing the beſt things with an indifferent Affection; and indifferent things, ſuch as wordly Goods, with our beſt Affection; or avoiding the leaſt Evils, ſuch as temporal Calamities, with our greateſt Hatred; and the greateſt Evils, <hi>viz.</hi> Sin, and eternal Death, with a leſs Hate, or Averſion; in any of theſe Miſcarriages, which (God knows) are but too frequent, we blindly run into ſinful Luſts.</p>
            <p>4thly. And Laſtly, The diſorderly Appetites of the Body, together with that of carnal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, may in a more peculiar manner; be called fleſhly Luſts; thus when we eat and drink more than is conſiſtent with our Health, <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 13. 14. Jer. 5. 8.</note> and the ſprightly Operations of the Soul, or when our carnal Concupiſcence is directed to a wrong Object, or immoderately uſed on a lawful one, they are in the very matter of them ſinful Luſts.</p>
            <p>And thus having enquired into the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Nature, 'tis not difficult to forebode what (without the Application of Religion) muſt be the unhappy Effects of them. It were eaſie to ſhew how every one of thoſe fleſhly Luſts in particular, reckoned up by the Apoſtle, flow from one or other of our diſordered and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152530:7"/> corrupted Faculties. But this were a task, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot very agreeable to my intended Brevity, ſo (I could hope) not very neceſſary, in as much <hi>as the Luſts of the Fleſh are manifeſt, which are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19. 20. 21.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſe, Adultery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs, Idolatry, Witchchraft, Hatred, Variance, Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, Envyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like, are the Luſts, which we muſt deny; that is, which we muſt avoid; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that not only in their groſſer Acts, but we muſt reſiſt and ſtifle (as much as poſſible) the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery firſt Motions in us; and in order thereto, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e muſt form before-hand firm and well-grounded Reſolutions never to yield them our Aſſent; and leſt our Reſolutions, <hi>when tryed</hi> ſhould not <hi>be found faithful,</hi> we ſhould prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off all Occaſion of Diſpute, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly ſhun even the very Shadow of a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. All this Care and Caution is implyed <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 22.</note> in this one word <hi>Deny.</hi> And thus we ſee what it is to deny Ungodlineſs and wordly Luſts, and that in effect it is the ſame as <hi>to Renounce the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinful Luſts of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſh,</hi> as our Church Catechiſm expreſſeth it; and this is one great Part of our <hi>Baptiſmal Vow.</hi> That which is further required of us to procure us a Right to the fore-mentioned Priviledges is, <hi>That we live Soberly Righteouſly and Godly in this preſent World; ſoberly</hi> in Relation to our ſelves, <hi>Righteouſly</hi> in reference to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and <hi>Godly</hi> in reſpect to God, which latter, being the Foundation of the other two, I ſhall beg leave to invert their Order, and begin with that firſt, which is here ſet laſt, and that is, the <hi>Living Godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Godlineſs (or as it here ſignifies) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Piety, hath (as I before hinted) a ſpecial Regard to thoſe Commands of God, which have a more immediate aſpect upon God himſelf, and ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152530:8"/> chiefly imports <hi>our duty towards God,</hi> the whole whereof is ſum'd up by the Author to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews in few words, namely, <hi>the believing that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>he is, and that he is a Rewarder of them that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſeek him.</hi> As to his Exiſtence, this I might evince from, not only his Works of Creation and Providence, but from the Nature and Dictates of every Mans Conſcience, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting to him, that God is <hi>not far from every</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 17. 27.</note> 
               <hi>one of us.</hi> Which gives me reaſonable grounds of hope, that my time and pains would be better ſpent in explaining his Eſſence, than in proving his Exiſtence, that is, in ſhewing you what he is, rather than that he is. Now God (as far as an infinite Being can be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or deſcribed by a finite Underſtanding) <hi>is a Spirit,</hi> the Creator of all things, Inviſible, <hi>whom no Man hath ſeen or can ſee.</hi> Omniſcient, <note place="margin">John 4. 24. Acts 17. 24. 1 Tim. 1. 17. 6. 16. Joh. 21. 17. 1 Sam. 2. 2. John 3. 33. Pſal. 90. 2. Jam. 1. 17. Gen. 17. 1. Pſal. 119. 68. Pſal. 139. 7. 145. 17. Deut. 7. 9. Exod. 34. 6. 1 Tim. 2. 5. 1 John 5. 7. John 4. 23, 24. Eph. 3. 14. 1 Col. 6. 20. Acts 20. 36. Rev. 4. 10, 11.</note> or <hi>knowing all things. Moſt Holy, True, Eternal, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable, Omnipotent.</hi> Perfectly <hi>Good,</hi> both in himſelf, and to us. <hi>Omnipreſent,</hi> or every where preſent. Moſt <hi>Juſt, Merciful and Loving;</hi> who, though <hi>one in Eſſence,</hi> exiſts in three Perſons, <hi>Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> from which (though imperfect) Account of the Divine Being, it is eaſie to deduce or draw our various Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him, as thus. Since from this Deſcription of God 'tis plain that we owe our ſelves unto him, we owe withal, all poſſible Service to him, which (to procure his divine Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance) muſt be ſuited to his Nature, and that being Spiritual, it follows that we muſt <hi>worſhip him in Spirit,</hi> or with a ſpiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that is, we muſt make all poſſible and juſt acknowledgments of the divine Perfections, chiefly by the Powers of our Souls, yet not excluding thoſe of our Bodies, with which we muſt <hi>glorify him,</hi> as well as <hi>with our Spirits,</hi> and that, by ſuch humble geſtures of Body, as teſtify and extoll the adorable Perfections of God to others; we muſt entertain right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the divine Nature and Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152530:8"/> in our Minds, frequently call them to mind, firmly believe them, really delight in <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25, 28.</note> them, and (as far as 'tis poſſible) imitate thoſe which are imitable by us. We muſt further, out of our great Eſteem for, and deep ſenſe of theſe his Excellencies, admire and adore him, <note place="margin">—18. 3. 96. 4. Heb 13. 15 Acts 17. 28.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow down our Souls before him in <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſes</hi> to him, as to our great Creator and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enefactor, <hi>in whom we</hi> continually <hi>live, move, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave our Beings.</hi> All this is no more than a juſt acknowledgment of what God is in himſelf, and here deſcribed to us; for thus our Faith and Hope, that is to ſay, our Aſſent to the <note place="margin">John 6. 40.</note> Truths, which he hath revealed, and our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of what he has promiſed, are debts <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 11.</note> we owe to his Veracity or Truth, as founded on his Omniſcience, Holineſs, and his Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence. Our love of, and truſt in him, are <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 3. 1. Tim. 4. 10. Iſa. 26. 4.</note> the neceſſary effects of our firm Belief of his Almighty Power, joyned with his infinite Goodneſs, which renders him both able and willing to do us good. Our fear of him or care not to offend him is but the natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 5.</note> of our Belief of his Omnipreſence, and Juſtice armed with his Omnipotence. Our patience and ſubmiſſion to his Will are but <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 9.</note> in us, the reaſonable products of his infinite Wiſdom and Greatneſs, exerted in his act of Creation. Our Honour or our profound Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30</note> and Reſpect to his ſuper-excellent Majeſty, and to all things relating to him, as his Name, his Word, his Sacraments, his Miniſters, his Houſe, and his Day, our profound Regard to theſe naturally flow from our conſideration of all his boundleſs Perfections.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, his Exiſting in three Perſons, <hi>Father,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 John 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> binds upon us freſh Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Obedience to them all, &amp; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of owning and renewing our Obligations and Reſolutions of Obedience to them. in the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lord's Supper.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152530:9"/> Becauſe herein we make a particular acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of what each of theſe bleſſed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have done for us; as that God the Father, who once <hi>gave his Son to die for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> is diſpoſed to preſent him here <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 8. 1 John 2. 2.</note> for our <hi>ſpiritual Food and Suſtenance.</hi> The Son, as he once <hi>freely offered up himſelf for us</hi> upon the Croſs; So again freely offers to us his <hi>Body</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 14-12. 2. Matth. 26. 27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>and Blood</hi> in this heavenly Feaſt. And Laſtly, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> conveys that ſtrength and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to our Souls, which is here received from the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> All which enhanſeth our Obligations to renew our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <note place="margin">Acts 2. 46. 1 Cor. 11. 26.</note> to them all, and in order thereto to come often to this Bleſſed Sacrament, for the worthy receiving whereof, the beſt Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to <hi>live Soberly, Righteouſly and Godly, in this preſent World.</hi> And what it is to live <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly</hi> is the ſecond thing to be conſider'd by me.</p>
            <p>Now Righteouſneſs is, in ſhort nothing elſe but the giving to every man his due, in all thoſe various capacities and relations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſtands. Thus there being the relation of Magiſtrate and Subject, of Paſtor and Flock, of Father and Son, of Husband and Wife, Maſter and Servant, Brethren and Friends, there being alſo a common Relation to all Mankind as our Neighbour, Righteouſneſs conſiſts in an exact obſervance, as well of thoſe ſpecial Duties, which each of theſe relations may bring us under in particular, as of all other Duties, which the common relation of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, lays upon us in general; that is, in the giving to every Man his due, not only as he is my Neighbour, but moreover and above, as he may be concerned with me in any one or more of the forementioned Relations. Thus <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1, 4. Eccleſ. 10. 20. Pro. 20. 20.</note> (beſides the common Obligation of Neighbour) our Superiors the Magiſtrates, being Gods Vicegerents, and of his Appointment and acting by his Authority juſtly claim of us an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152530:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wful Apprehenſion of them in our Thoughts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e making an honourable mention of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith our Lips, ſubmiting to them for <hi>Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> paying them their <hi>Tribute,</hi> and praying for <note place="margin">Acts 23. 5. Jud. 8. 1 Pet. 2. 13. Rom. 13. 5. 7. 1 Tim. 2. 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir happy Government of us, &amp; that, which in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urn they owe unto their Subjects, is their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ction againſt the Aſſaults of their Enemies, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtant maintenance of their Rights &amp; Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, their Liberty and Religion, <hi>that under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we may lead quiet and peaceable Lives in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> And as to our ſpiritual <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 13. 1 Tim. 5. 17. Heb. 13. 17</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ents who have <hi>begotten us through the Goſpel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> alſo we muſt <hi>eſteem very highly in love for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir Works Sake,</hi> and if <hi>they rule well count them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thy of double Honour;</hi> which we cannot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> expreſs, than by <hi>attending to their Word and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctrine</hi> with the utmoſt Application of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inds, and by falling to the practice of it <note place="margin">John 20. 23. 1 Cor. 16. 16. Gal. 6. 6.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith all our Hearts; which would not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>event the ungrateful uſe of the Cenſures of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urch, (which we muſt ſubmit unto when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end) but would better diſpoſe us to afford <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r Paſtors an honourable maintenance, <hi>as it is our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ties to do,</hi> it being (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays) a matter <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 14</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God's own <hi>Ordaining</hi> and Appointment <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Laſtly, we muſt joyn with them in their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 25 Luk. 2. 37. Acts 2. 46. 1 Theſſ. 5. 17.</note> up the publick Prayers of the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ily preſent our private Prayers to God for them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or good Succeſs on their Labours, <hi>that whilſt they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch to others, they themſelves may not be caſt away;</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her <hi>may both ſave themſelves, &amp; them that hear them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Our natural Parents, being (under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d) the Authors and Maintainers of our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gs, acquire hereby a right to our Honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l Eſteem, our Fear and Reverence, our <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 19</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve and Affection, our Obedience to their <note place="margin">Col. 3. 20.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ful Commands, our ſubmiſſion to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtiſements, and laſtly our Gratitude in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>niſtring <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 9. 1 Tim. 5. 4.</note> to their Wants, and bearing with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Infirmities. And they, as being our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152530:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152530:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152530:11"/> are by the Laws both of Nature and Religion, obliged to provide their Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as far as they are able) with a competent maintenance, in reſpect both of their Souls and Bodies. In reſpect to their Souls, that they be brought to an early Baptiſm, that they be <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 4.</note> taught to read, and as ſoon as poſſible, be inſtructed in the Principles of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that a conſtant care be had, (by <hi>forbearing Provocations, and ſhewing Piety at Home,</hi> and by all other good and prudent means) tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they dayly encreaſe in the Knowledge and Practice of them. In reſpect to their Bodies that their Parents ſupply them with <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Raiment,</hi> and (if poſſible) with all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, as well as Neceſſaries, of Life; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 14.</note> they may be put into the World under a poſſibility, and probability of thriving in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>There are alſo mutual dues between Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife, and the Duties common t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them both are, that they love each other, and expreſs it in endeavouring to procure a mutua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſatisfaction in all things, and to promote th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 31</note> Temporal and Spiritual Welfare of each other; that they be faithful to each othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bed, having always in remembrance the 7th Commandment; that they bear with eac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">—5. 1 Cor. 2. 7 1 Pet. 3. 2. Heb. 13. 4. 1 Pet. 3. 7.</note> others Infirmities, and partake of each other Proſperity or Adverſity; that they pray fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> each other, that they honour, that is, giveth reſpect due to each others Perſon, and particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larly that the Husband <hi>give Honour to the Wife</hi> in St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſenſe, which is <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Pet. 3. 7</note> Maintenance, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> being the weaker Veſſel;</hi> that he exerciſe his Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority over Her in the milder way of Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, rather than in the more imperious wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Command, remembring that <hi>they twain are bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one fleſh,</hi> though <hi>the Man be the head of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man;</hi> that he <hi>gives her all due Benevolence,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 3.—7. 3</note> laſtly all ſeaſonable and neceſſary Inſtructions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Duties of the Wife, whereby ſhe ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152530:11"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e eſpecially obliged unto her Husband, are <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Eph. 5. 24.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe ſubmits peaceably to that Authority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her, which God has given to the Man; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as a neceſſary conſequence of this, <hi>She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce her Husband,</hi> and ſhew it in a becoming <note place="margin">—33. 1 Pet. 3. 4.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>guage, and Deportment towards him; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly, that ſhe be at all times forward to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t (ſhe knows) he likes, and obey what he <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 24.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mands, provided it be both lawful and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>edient, of which, he is ſuppoſed to be the moſt <note place="margin">Col. 3. 18. 1 Cor. 14. 35.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>petent Judge, being by the Apoſtle appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an Inſtructor to his Wife, even in Matters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, there are various Duties incumbent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maſters, and Servants, that Maſters take a due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of their Servatnts as Members of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n Families; that they provide for their <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dies a competent Maintenance, and for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uls, religious Inſtruction and Admonition; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at in every reſpect <hi>they give to their Servants,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t which is juſt and equal, as knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they alſo have a Maſter in Heaven with whom is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſpect of Perſons.</hi> That they be not in their <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 11.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>overnment of them <hi>harſh and froward,</hi> but <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld and gentle;</hi> that they require nothing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em, but that which is, in it ſelf, both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nable and lawful; that they threaten them <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 9.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o more than is neceſſary, and give them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (when need ſo requires) <hi>due</hi> Correction; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they perfectly inſtruct them in the Art or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rade, which they undertook to teach them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they reward them according to agreement, <note place="margin">Deut. 24. 14, 15. Jam. 5. 4.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nctually paying them their Wages; laſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they reſtrain them from Vicious, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove them (all they can) to Religious Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s: And Servants in return of theſe Dues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt (as they juſtly ought) <hi>count ſuch Maſters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 1.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rthy of all Honour,</hi> and ſhew it upon all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons in their reſpectfull Carriage and Demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our towards them. <hi>They muſt obey them in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ings,</hi> agreeable to their Contract, &amp; that out of a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152530:12"/> Principle of <hi>Conſcience, not with Eye-ſervice as Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 22. Eph. 6. 5. 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>pleaſers, but as the Servants of Chriſt, with ſingl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs of heart</hi> and chearfulneſs of Spirit; whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will make them diligent &amp; conſtant in their Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience; they muſt be alſo true to their Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 9, 10</note> ever promoting, by all lawful means, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maſters Profit; they muſt take care of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goods, vindicate their Credit abroad (as far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they can) and conceal their Infirmities at hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And laſtly, they muſt quietly ſubmit to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unjuſt as well as <hi>due</hi> Corrections, ever amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing by them; <hi>for what glory is it, if when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are buffeted for your faults, ye ſhall take it patien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? but if when ye do well, and ſuffer for it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>take it patiently, this is acceptable unto God.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordingly Servants are there commanded <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſubject to their Maſters, with all fear, not only to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good and gentle, but alſo to the froward.</hi> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though Maſters ſhould not ſtrictly obſerve thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duties to their Servants, yet this would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> free Servants from their Obligations to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maſters; becauſe God has in Duty bound no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only the Maſter and Servant to one another but both of them to himſelf. And this, (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would have it obſerved and remembred) hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true in all the other forementioned Relation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Superiors and Inferiors; ſo that the Supe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rior's offence againſt God, in depriving the In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferior of his due, (and ſo on the contrary) can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not authorize the Inferior to ſin againſt Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> too, by returning the injury received upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuperior; as for inſtance, though a wicked Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhould caſt off all care of his helpleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Children, and ſo ſin againſt God, as well as injure his Children, (who have a natural righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to maintenance) yet this would not excuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Children from their Obedience to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wicked Father; becauſe it is impoſſible tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever one Man's Sin ſhould excuſe that of ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, when both ſin againſt God. And this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 25</note> all I think neceſſary to be ſaid concerning the Relations of Superiors and Inferiors
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152530:12"/> There are other Relations, which ſeem to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e upon the level, thoſe, I mean of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en; and as to theſe, there are ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ar dues belonging to them, whether they be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>natural</hi> or our <hi>ſpiritual Brethren.</hi> Thus our <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ral Brethren</hi> are, by means of their near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ance to us by nature, obliged to be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iceable to us (when they can) than they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bound to be to mere Strangers; becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>natural Affection</hi> for us may be well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed to prompt them to it, by exciting in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n a paſſionate concern for our Welfare; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich ſuperſedes the want of all thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ts and Entreaties, which are allowable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſometimes neceſſary to be uſed, in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out our relief to Strangers. So that to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our Brother of our Subſtance, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him in every thing where we can, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere he needeth, ſeemeth to be but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ary, though juſt, effect of our near Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to him by Nature. And no leſs neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> natural is a mutual accord and agreement <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ongſt Brethren, and that upon account of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r partaking of the ſame Blood and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce, deriving both from the ſame Root, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as a Conſequence of this, from their like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of temper (for the moſt part) from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ir equality in circumſtances, and from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>earments of innocent and undeſigned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ation; all which diſpoſeth them to delight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine anothers Converſe, freely to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e their Thoughts, and ſo participate of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thers Souls as much as they do, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r Bodies; ſo that <hi>Nature it ſelf teacheth us,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Brethren owe to one another love, and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effect of that, union in Heart and Soul; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the effect of both theſe, a readineſs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ply their Wants, either by lending them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bodily Aſſiſtance, or <hi>Miniſtring to them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Subſtance,</hi> which is by the Apoſtle called <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oviding for thoſe of our own Houſe</hi> or Family.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152530:13"/> But beſides our <hi>Brethren by Nature,</hi> there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> alſo ſuch <hi>by Grace,</hi> commonly called <hi>Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Brethren,</hi> who become ſuch, by being made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſm <hi>Members</hi> of the ſame <hi>Catholick Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with our ſelves; we being all united un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>one head Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And in this Relation th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 5. 1 Cor. 12. 12, 13.</note> are various Duties we ſtand obliged to obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> towards one another. For, conſidering that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are <hi>Members of the ſame Body,</hi> we muſt ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> think our ſelves bound to contribute, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can, both, to the Service of the <hi>Members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> particular,</hi> and of the whole Body in gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for as 'tis in the <hi>natural Body,</hi> ſo is it in <hi>the ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al One,</hi> every <hi>Member</hi> is uſeful to, and recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 21.</note> benefit from another. <hi>The Eye cannot ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Hand, I have no need of thee; nor again; the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the Feet, I have no need of you;</hi> ſo that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> comes our indiſpenſable Duty, as <hi>Members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Catholick Church,</hi> to render our ſelves as u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, as we can, to all our <hi>fellow Memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> having the ſame care one for another;</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould exerciſe in mutual Offices of kindn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to one another, as occaſion ſerves, being obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged <hi>to do good unto all Men,</hi> but (as the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> obſerves) more <hi>eſpecially unto them that are of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Houſhold of Faith;</hi> to relieve at once the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> of their Bodies and promote the good of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Souls; to <hi>admoniſh</hi> them of their Faults, bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 15 Rom. 15. 14. Gal.. 6. Rom 15. 1. 1 Cor. 1. 10.—12. 25.</note> them to a Sorrow for them, and an ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of them; <hi>to bear with the infirmities of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> weak Bretheren;</hi> to convince thoſe that ſepar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from the Church, of the Sin and Miſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Schiſm;</hi> to perſuade them to an immedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> return into the Boſom of the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſtant adherence to her. To communic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with them in all the common Offices of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anity, in adhering to the ſame Faith a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Doctrine, that Faith I mean, <hi>which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> once delivered to the Saints,</hi> in joyning in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſame Worſhip, receiving the ſame Sacram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> of the Lords Supper, in offering up the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152530:13"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ayers, the ſame in ſubſtance though not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e forms of expreſſion, being preſented to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſame God, for the ſame common Mercies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on the ſame terms, through the ſame <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2 5.</note> and with the ſame common Affection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Brotherly concern for one another: And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e are thus to communicate with our <hi>fellow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbers</hi> in matters of religions Worſhip: So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt we alſo participate of their Joys and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrows, whether in temporal or ſpiritual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncerns; for as the <hi>Members</hi> of the Body <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al</hi> communicate their Sorrows and their Joys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the reſt; So the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dy muſt ſympathize with one another, and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ether one Member ſuffer, all the Members ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12, 26 Rom. 12. 24.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fer with it,</hi> or <hi>whether one Member be honoured, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Members ſhould rejoyce with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, as we are thus to partake of the Joys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Sorrows of the <hi>Members in particular:</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo of thoſe of the Church <hi>in general,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er national or univerſal. In times of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution we muſt condole the Deſolations. Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r Miſeries and Calamities ſhould, more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecially, excite both <hi>our pity to ſee her in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt,</hi> and our Repentance of our crying Sins, <note place="margin">Pſal. 102. 14. Hoſea. 5. 15. Pſal. 51. 18</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich juſtly draw down direful Judgments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n her. Earneſtly beſeeching God that <hi>he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> good in his good pleaſure unto Sion, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould build up the Walls of Jeruſalem.</hi> And in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er flouriſhing Condition, we muſt rejoyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith <hi>Her,</hi> expreſſing our Joy and Gratitude in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithful Obedience to, as well as in a conſtant Communion with <hi>Her,</hi> that God may be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſpoſed to hear our Prayers, which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould ever offer up on <hi>Her</hi> behalf, ſaying, <hi>O</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 74. 19</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eliver not the Soul of thy Turtle Dove unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ultitude of the wicked, forget not the Congregation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thy poor for ever, but ſtrengthen thy Spouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, There is one Relation more, which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall mention to you, and that is, a very Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate one, I mean that of a Friend, <hi>who is as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 6.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152530:14"/> 
               <hi>ones own Soul;</hi> and though this Relation Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anity calls by the name of Charity, (which, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch, is to be extended to all Mankind) yet be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe our Capacities are finite, and we canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exerciſe thoſe Offices of Friendſhip to all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World, which we can to ſome few particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Perſons; therefore this Frindſhip or particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Charity, muſt be confined to thoſe few, whom either the convenience of Neighbourhood the Probability of their Uſefulneſs, our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Relation to them, our delight in them, our ſpecial Affection for them, and above all their known Worth and Goodneſs ſhall invite us, to admit into our Friendſhip; and when upon any, or all of the fore-going Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we have made ſome few Perſons our Friends, then Chriſtianity, as well as the nature of Friendſhip requires, that we love our Friend with the greateſt Affection; that <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 17.</note> we ſerve him to the utmoſt of our Power; that we freely communicate our Thoughts to him, when there be occaſion; that we adviſe <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 9.</note> him in his Doubts and Scruples; that we <hi>admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him of his Faults,</hi> reſtrain him from Evil; faithfully keep his Secrets; that we comfort <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 22. 22.</note> him in Afflictions, rejoyce with him in Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, doubling his Joys and dividing his Griefs; that we heartily wiſh and pray for his Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 10.</note> and laſtly, that we be conſtant to his Friendſhip, and all theſe Offices of it. All this is (as I before hinted) Charity extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Few. But Chriſtian Charity is in its own nature much more comprehenſive, and takes in all Mankind; for ſo the Goſpel enjoyns us, to <hi>love our Neighbour as our ſelves.</hi> And <note place="margin">Matt. 22. 39.</note> in the Scripture ſenſe, whoſoever is another; is our Neighbour; ſo that, according to the Chriſtian Law, we muſt do all the good we <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 24.</note> can to all men, not only Friends, but Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whoſe injuries muſt never be otherwiſe <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 20, 21.</note> return'd than with Prayers and Kindneſs, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152530:14"/> muſt forgive them as heartily as we deſire to be forgiven, and deal by them (as well as by all other Men) as kindly, and as juſtly as we deſire to be dealt by, for this is the great Rule of the Goſpel, and of Univerſal, as well as of eternal Obligation, <hi>All things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 12.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> So that if we would not be abuſed, &amp; injured in our Perſons, robbed or plunder'd in our Eſtates, over-reached in our Bargains, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered or defamed in our good Name, or the like: So neither muſt we offer any of theſe or the like Abuſes to any Man, whether Friend or Foe, but as in reaſon we deſire to avoid Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to have our Rights defended, and nothing of them loſt; ſo muſt we, in our Obſervance of this equitable Rule, not only not injure, but maintain and defend our Neighbour in all his Rights, as far as we can, otherwiſe we are not juſt unto him. For if the Nature of Juſtice be the giving to every Man his due, then the Practice of it muſt certainly conſiſt in never taking away, but preſerving (what we can) the Life of our Neighbour, in defending his Body from Injuries, and his Soul from Sin, in granting him the Liberty of reaſoning and judging for himſelf, in not ſlandering him, or <note place="margin">James 4. 11</note> leſſening his good Name, but as far as we can in clearing it when it is aſperſed, in imparting <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſal 15. 2, 3-4. Jer. 33. 15, 16. Lev. 19. 13. Mark 10. 19. 1 Theſſ. 4. 6</note> our true meaning to him by our Words, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming punctually what we promiſed to him, in fairly uſing him in our Dealings, in never coveting his Goods, but rather deſiring to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Profit. In theſe and ſuch like things conſiſts our juſtice to him; becauſe he being a rational Creature united to us in Society, holds his Life, his Body and Soul, with all the Benefits of Society, ſuch as Truth, Love, Peace, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Protection, and the Profits of Trade, by the ſame Law of Nature with our ſelves, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152530:15"/> ſo can make as good a Title to them, as we can to what we have; ſo that according to the ſtated Notion of Juſtice, and this unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Law of Equity, the <hi>doing as we would be done by,</hi> we can no more injure our Neighbour than our ſelves, but are ſtrictly bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his forementioned Rights, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to free him (when we can) from thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and Misfortunes, which either do, or would invade them.</p>
            <p>And though this is often called by another name, I mean, that of Charity, yet it ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Nature of Juſtice; it being no more than the miſerable Man's due (as by conſequence it appears) to receive relief from his Fellow Creatures, when it can be had. And to this Notion the Pſalmiſt ſeems to incline, when he gives the Charitable Man (as he does very oft <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 21. 25. 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> in the Pſalms) the Name and Title of <hi>Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Juſtice to our Neighbour obligeth us to relieve the various Neceſſities of the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whether they relate to the Soul or Body. In regard to the Soul, ſorrow of Mind juſtly <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 14. James 5. 19. 20. Rom. 14. 19 2 Tim. 2. 24, 25. Rom. 15. 1, 2. Acts 20. 35 Pſal. 41. 1. Luk. 10. 33, 34, 35, 37. James 2. 15. 16. 1 John 17, 18.</note> demands our Adminiſtration of Comfort; Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Error calls for our Information and Forbearance; Perverſeneſs and Obſtinacy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will for our wholeſom Advice and ſeaſonable Reproof, Weakneſs of Judgment for our Direction, Pity and Compaſſion. And as to the Body, its natural Blemiſhes and Defects ought in juſtice to ſollicite more our Pity than our Scorn or Laughter; its Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; Infirmities ſhould ſtir us up to contribute all we can to its ſupport and recovery, and as for its outward wants, Food and Raiment, theſe call loudly for our Supply, as being neceſſary to the Preſervation of the Individual. Now in ſupplying our Neighbour (that is, every Man that wanteth) with all theſe things, as far as our Abilities will ſerve, or his Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties require, is that Duty of Charity, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152530:15"/> Juſtice obligeth us to exerciſe towards him.</p>
            <p>And thus in a faithful diſcharge of all the forementioned dues to our Neighbour, in all his Capacities and Relations, conſiſteth this great Duty of Righteouſneſs, or living Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p>The laſt Duty to be conſidered is, that which reſpecteth our ſelves, (and that is) the living Soberly. By <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sobriety,</hi> I underſtand a Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Faculties of the Soul, and the Powers of the Body, to the Rules of right Reaſon, and the Laws of God; that is, that we employ our Underſtandings in ſearching <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 15, 27. Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9. 2 Chron. 20, 20. Pſal. 37. 4. Pſ. 119. 127 Mat. 22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Col. 3. 2. 1 John 2. 15.</note> out the nobleſt Truths and our chief End, which are God and Happineſs; that we bend and diſpoſe our Wills to proſecute our chief End by the fitteſt Means, that is, by the Practice of Religion; that we proportion our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Value of things; that is, that we ſet our beſt Affections on the beſt things; <hi>that we love the Lord our God with all our Heart, with all our Soul, and with all our Mind,</hi> and beſtow no greater Affection on the things of this World, than their intrinſick Worth requires; that we hate and avoid the greateſt Evils, Sin and Death, with our utmoſt Hatred; that we <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 28</note> be leſs fearful of leſs Misfortunes, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffer thoſe that are unavoidable; that <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 1. Heb. 13. 5. Eph. 4. 31.</note> we envy not the Fortunate, or <hi>covet</hi> any thing that is our Neighbours, but content our ſelves with what we have; that we revenge not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, or grow angry at Contempt; but ſhew forth <hi>the Fruits of the Spirit in Peace, long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 22.</note> 
               <hi>gentleneſs, goodneſs and meekneſs.</hi> That we va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not our ſelves above the real Merits of thoſe <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 5. Phil. 2. 3 Rom. 12. 10 1 Pet. 2. 11. 1 Cor. 9. 25. 1 Cor. 6. 18 1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> Gifts, which either Nature, Grace, or Fortune hath beſtowed upon us. That we reſtrain our bodily Appetites from the exceſſive uſe of Meat and Drink, and Venery; that we indulge them no farther than anſwering the End for which they were given us, which is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152530:16"/> of Nature and the Preſervation of Mankind, and not, (as too many make them) the unhappy Occaſions of thoſe notorious and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9, 10. Mat. 5. 27, 28. Rom. 13. 13</note> crying Sins, Drunkenneſs, Gluttony, and Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Laſtly, that we be moderate in the Uſe and Enjoyment of Pleaſures and Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, enjoying them no further than as they ſerve to refreſh our wearied Bodies, and reſtore the languid Faculties of our Souls, to their ſprightly Operations. In a due Obſervance of all theſe things conſiſts the great Duty of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</hi> And theſe I take to be the beſt Proofs <hi>of a</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſound Mind,</hi> which is what the Greek and original Word ſignifieth.</p>
            <p>And thus having ſhewn you what it is to <hi>deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, and wordly Luſts, and what to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent World,</hi> I am to tell you next, that <hi>This do and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 10. 28</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt live;</hi> the Practice of theſe Duties will moſt certainly give you abundant Reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect with Comfort; or <hi>look for the bleſſed Hope</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and glorious Appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore this, amongſt other Arguments, is what I would inſiſt upon, to preſs you to the faithful Obſervance of the forementioned Duties. But beſides this great and general Motive, there are ſome other To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of Argument, or Heads of Diſcourſe, by which I intend (more largely in my Sermons) to diſſuade you from the foremention'd Sins, and perſuade you to the Practice of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties.</p>
            <p>And my Diſſuaſions from theſe Sins ſhall be drawn,</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the great Slavery and Drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Luſts and Vices.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From the Conſideration of their being the moſt diſingenous, and ungrateful Returns of the moſt ineſtimable Mercies.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152530:16"/>
            <p> Thirdly, From the Conſideration of their being very prejudicial to all Societies.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, From the ill Effects they have upon our Souls, Bodies and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Fithly, And Laſtly, from the Certainty of their betraying Men into eternal Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the other World.</p>
            <p>And my Perſuaſions to the Duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall be taken.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From their Agreableneſs to the preſent Circumſtances of humane Nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From this Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> that theſe Duties of Religion directly conſult the Good of our Souls, Bodies, and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, From the Conſideration that there are great Aſſiſtances given us, to render theſe Duties not only eaſie, but pleaſant to us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, And Laſtly, that the Practice of our Duty is the indiſpenſable Condition of our future Happineſs, the only ground upon which we can reaſonably <hi>look for that bleſſed Hope and the glorious Appearing of the great God and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I would diſſuade you from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Sins, upon Conſideration of the great Slavery and Drudgery of them. Thus the impious diſowning God in our Thoughts, and the more monſtrous Denial of him in our Actions, fills the Mind with ſuch uneaſie Scruples and Horrors, as are never to be ſtifled; Mens vain and unneceſſary Curioſity ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to puff them up with Pride, which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 2</note> oppoſite to the Charity that edifieth;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152530:17"/> and therefore when Men are not content to reſt <hi>in the plain wholeſom Words of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> they are ſcarce fit for humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; becauſe by being <hi>Proud and doting about queſtions and ſtrifes of Words,</hi> they unhappily oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion <hi>envy, ſtrife, railings, evil ſurmiſings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe diſputings of Men of corrupt Minds,</hi> and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth his Son Timothy <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>from ſuch to withdraw himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the Diſorders of our Wills, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Miſery under the falſe Appearance of Good, rob us of our true Satisfaction, and in exchange thereof give us nothing but real diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments. And ſo Men's inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires hurry them upon ſtrange and unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Attempts, betray them into Injuſtice, Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Revenge, beſides the many diſtracting Cares and Fears, to which, at the ſame time, they expoſe their unhappy Souls. Laſtly, their rebellious Luſts and Appetites put them often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon hard Service, make them toil and ſweat for the gratification of them, and ſo in a literal ſenſe they become mere Slaves and Drudges to them, and accordingly the holy Scriptures repreſent ſuch Men as <hi>wearying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>to commit Iniquity,</hi> and <hi>to labour in the very Fire,</hi> to <hi>ſpend their Strength for nought, to ſell themſelves</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21. 25. John 8. 34.</note> (as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Ahab) to work Wickedneſs.</hi> So true is our Saviour's Aſſertion, <hi>whoſoever committeth Sin is the Servant of Sin,</hi> a Servant too that gets no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his Pains, but <hi>ſpends his Labour for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 2.</note> 
               <hi>that which ſatisfieth not.</hi> For <hi>what Fruit had ye of thoſe things whereof ye are now aſhamed;</hi> ſays <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 21.</note> the Apoſtle to thoſe who had once been the Servants of Sin, for <hi>End of thoſe things is Death.</hi> Nothing you ſee, but <hi>Shame and Death</hi> is to be gotten by ſuch unprofitable Service, and theſe will prove but a ſorry Recompence for all that Labour and Vexation, which you ſee the Sinner muſt be condemned unto, in the Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his Luſts.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152530:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider again, that they are the <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 6.</note> moſt diſingenuous and ungrateful Returns of the moſt numerous and ineſtimable Mercies. God's Redemption of the World, by the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Death of his Son, is an admirable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Love of both to Mankind, and <note place="margin">John 3. 16.</note> received no little Addition, by being free on their Part, and undeſerved on ours; they had <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 24.—5. 6, 7, 8. Job 22. 2, 3.</note> no Intereſt to promote, no by ends to ſerve, nothing inviting in us, no Argument of any ſort to move them to it, but only infinite Kindneſs and Compaſſion, beholding the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of wretched Humanity, diſpoſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">1 John 4. 9. 10. Ez. 16. 6. Iſa. 53. 4, 5, 6.</note> to ſend his only begotten Son, and the Son to take upon him our Miſeries, make them his own, and that too, by <hi>dying</hi> for us that were <hi>his Enemies,</hi> and yet <hi>dying</hi> for us, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us the greateſt Bleſſings, ſuch as a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the Power and Puniſhment of our <note place="margin">Mat. 1. 21. Heb. 2. 14, 15. 1 Theſſ. 1. 10. Tit. 2. 4. Heb. 5. 9.</note> Sins, from the Malice of Satan, from the Sting of Death, and to ſettle us in a ſtate of Holineſs here, and Happineſs hereafter. Now there is nothing can thwart this generous Love, or baffle all it's gracious Deſigns, but our Sins; which are ſo contrary to the Purity of his Divine Nature, as well as to his gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns upon us, that he cannot but <hi>hate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 4. Heb. 6. 6. Eph. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>them.</hi> They <hi>wound and crucifie his Son afreſh</hi> they <hi>vex and grieve his holy Spirit,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to entertain them againſt all theſe endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obligations to the contrary, would be monſtrous Ingratitude, ſuch as wants a Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, and was <hi>never named among the Gentiles;</hi> for what greater Argument, can we have of our Inſenſibility of the Divine Favours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, if theſe inexpreſſible ones cannot work upon our Ingenuity ſo far, as to baniſh our Luſts, thoſe implacable Enemies both to God, and <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 28, 29.</note> our own Souls; we are certainly loſt to all that is tender and apprehenſive in humane Nature, if ſuch mighty Benefits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152530:18"/> move us, to expreſs our grateful ſenſe of them, in ſuitable returns of Care and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, not only to <hi>abſtain from thoſe fleſhly Luſts, which war againſt the Soul,</hi> but to exchange them <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 11.</note> for ſuch good Diſpoſitions, as may move us to expreſs our thankfulneſs to God for all his Benefits, in Arts of new Obedience to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it may be further conſidered that theſe Luſts and Vices, which I am now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading you to <hi>deny,</hi> are very prejudicial to all Societies; for beſides that they juſtly expoſe Men to the Judgments of God, <hi>Who turns a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Land into Barreneſs, for the Wickedneſs of them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 107. 34.</note> 
               <hi>that dwell therein,</hi> they have a natural tendency to introduce Miſchief. Thus it's evident with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further proof of Argument, that Drunkenneſs, Gluttony and Whoredom, breed <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 21, 29, 30.—7. 26.</note> Diſeaſes, which weaken the Force and Strength of a Nation; Malice, Envy and Revenge ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Men very troubleſome to others, as well as to themſelves, turn them into Beaſts of Prey, fit them more for a <hi>Den of Lyons,</hi> Wolves and Tygers, than the Society of rational Creatures; <note place="margin">James 3. 16.</note> and ſo Pride, Covetouſneſs, Injuſtice and Perfidiouſneſs adminiſter occaſion of Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſet men directly together by the Ears, ſo much reaſon have we to anſwer or reſolve St. <hi>James</hi> his Queſtion in the Affirmative, <hi>from whence come Wars and Fightings among you, come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">James 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>they not hence, even from your Luſts which war in your Members?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Men's Luſts have thus a very ill In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon them, as private Members of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety: So they fail not to communicate their Malignity to them in their publick Capacities, as Governours; for when Magiſtrates are not <hi>juſt, ruling in the Fear of God,</hi> they weaken their Authority, leſſen themſelves in the Eyes of their People, and make their Subjects very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152530:18"/> and unmanageable; and on the other hand, when Subjects by ſubmitting to their Luſts, violate and abuſe their Conſcience, they deprive the Publick of it's beſt Security of their Obedience. For this is the only firm and laſting Principle of Obedience, which can hold Men faſt, when all other Obligations to it, will fly in pieces. He that is Subject <hi>only for Wrath, and not for Conſcience ſake,</hi> will be ſure to ſubmit no longer than till he can reſiſt with Safety. But he that is ſubject <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> will continue ſo, as long as his Conſcience keeps up her Authority, which when his Luſts have once dethroned, then farewel all Submiſſion and Obedience; nothing then ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds but <hi>Strife, and Contention, and every evil</hi> 
               <note place="margin">James 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Work;</hi> and this will turn to our own great Diſadvantage, being by Nature not only fitted for, but made to ſtand in need of, thoſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Society of which our Luſts are very deſtructive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Ye may pleaſe to conſider further, that Ungodlineſs and wordly Luſts have very ill Effects upon the Souls, Bodies and Eſtates of Men. Thus as to the Soul, Senſuality and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance naturally darken the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18, 19.</note> for theſe by overcharging Nature load the animal Spirits, keep them low, and render them groſs, which by being low, caſt a Damp upon the Soul, and hinder her in her ſprightly Operations. So Anger, Envy, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Revenge pervert our Judgments, raiſe ſuch Prejudices in our Minds, as hinder our clear and due Perceptions of things. Senſual Pleaſures and Delights overcaſt the Mind with ſuch thick Miſts of Darkneſs, that neither are our Underſtandings able to diſcern, or our Wills to perſue, their true and chief Good. <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 15.</note> Laſtly, the extravagant Motions of our wild Affections, and the Rebellions of our brutiſh
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152530:19"/> Appetites againſt our Reaſon, hurry us into all manner of unaccountable Follies, make us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our ſelves, and diſpoſe us to act <hi>like the Beaſts that periſh.</hi> Beſides many other neceſſary, but uneaſie Effects of theſe Diſorders, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences offered to our Reaſon, ſuch are the ungrateful Recoilings of Nature, the uneaſie and perpetual Struglings between the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>the Spirit.</hi> The miſerable Diſtractions of their Minds which are drawn firſt one way and then another by contrary and impetuous Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the great and juſt confuſion of Face, Shame, and Self-condemnation, the continual frettings at their paſt Follies, their grievous Suſpicions of an After-reckoning, their inſupportable Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 14. Iſa. 57. 20. 21.</note> and anguiſh of Mind, ariſing from their unwelcome Reflections on their paſt Guilt, theſe are ſuch intolerable Miſchiefs, as are enough to diſcourage the moſt daring Sinner, from giving any longer Entertainment to thoſe Luſts, which are the unhappy cauſes of them; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if it be conſidered,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That they incommode not only our Souls, but our Bodies too, by robbing them of their Health and Eaſe together. Thus the forementioned Vices, Luxury, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Wantonneſs have a natural Tendency to ruin our Stomachs, ſpoil our Digeſtion, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our Blood, conſume our Spirits, and waſte our Strength. Envy, Malice, Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and Paſſion rot our Bones, ſour the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſtir them up to Exceſs, and put the <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 30.</note> whole Body into Combuſtion. Covetouſneſs with all it's Train of carking cares and diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thoughts, drives away Sleep, one of the ſupports of Nature, oppreſſes the Heart, damps the Spirits, ſets the Humors upon the Fret, and in what can we think all theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders ſhould end, but in all manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> Paroxyſms, Epilepſes, Catarhs, and I know not what hard Names, and harder things,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152530:19"/> as being the natural Effects of theſe Luſts, And theſe ill Effects me thinks ſhould the more effectually prevail with wicked Men to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their Sins by how much the more they value their Bodies above their Souls, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may well be ſuppoſed to uſe more care, in ſhunning thoſe Things, which are deſtructive to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It may be conſider'd alſo that your Luſts will as certainly ruin your Eſtates, as they do your Bodies, or your Souls, and that not only by haſtening the juſt Judgments of <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 21.</note> God upon them, but by that natural Tendency which there is in ſome particular Vices to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them. I need to inſtance only in Senſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and Revenge; as to the former I will leave you to judge, whether men cannot by eating fine, and drinking hard, and uſing their Palates to both, (and ſo render the Gratification of them neceſſary) whether they cannot by theſe means ſooner ſpend an Eſtate than ſatiate their <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 17.</note> craving Appetites. For an Eſtate though large, is yet limited, but ſo are not our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and therefore the one muſt needs be much ſooner ſpent, than the other. As to our Revenge, how chargeable the Gratification of that is, every Lawyer can inform you, and now ſince it is ſo chargeable to be wicked, our <hi>Luſts</hi> being very expenſive to us, 'tis undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ill Husbandry, and therefore worth no Mans while, to give them Entertainment, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially conſidering in the</p>
            <p>Laſt place, what is worſt of all, and that is, that they moſt certainly betray men into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruin and Deſtruction in the other World. For miſery (as ye have partly ſeen) is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Conſequence of Wickedneſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will be ſo in all Places, and at all times; ſo that Men's Luſts and Vicees which they have cheriſhed in this World, accompanying <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> their Souls into the other, will ſtill work the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152530:20"/> ſame direful Effects upon them as they did here, only with this Difference, that whereas they have here ſome refreſhing Intermiſſions, ſome little Diverſion from the foremention'd Miſeries, they will there be continual and heighten'd to the utmoſt Capacities of their Souls to receive them. So that the unhappy Sufferers will be condemned to lye roaring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Racks of their guilty Minds, without Intermiſſion, and without end. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are in the Scripture aſſured, that <hi>the Worm there never dieth, nor the Fire ever quenched,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mark 9. 44. Rev. 20. 10.</note> but that <hi>they are tormented Day and Night for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and ever.</hi> And yet this is to be the Portion of thoſe <hi>that live after the Fleſh,</hi> ſo that he <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 13.</note> who indulgeth his Luſts and Vices here muſt expect no Indulgence or Favour from God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; for <hi>know ye not that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>not inherit the Kingdom of God? be not deceived, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Effeminate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God;</hi> but what is worſe, ſhall have their Portion aſſigned them in that diſmal <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 46</note> Place, <hi>where there is nothing but Weeping, Wailing and Gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> Conſider ſeriouſly of theſe things, and then tell me whether ye have not ſufficient reaſon to <hi>Deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, and wordly Luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as this is the leaſt Part of our Duty; So the greateſt Motives are yet to be propoſed to you, thoſe I mean which are to encourage you to <hi>live Soberly, Righteouſly and Godly, in this preſent World.</hi> And here it may be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Obſervance of theſe Duties is very agreeable to the preſent Circumſtances of our humane Nature. Thus our Duties towards God, as owning him in our Thoughts, Words, and Actions, hearing his holy Word, Praying
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152530:20"/> to him and receiving the Sacrament, are all eaſie to be performed by us, and very benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to us when they are performed. Our <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 8.</note> Juſtice to our Neighbour in all his Capacities and Relations; and our Charity to him in all his Neceſſities, naturally tend to our Good, both as private Perſons &amp; as Members of Society. As private Perſons, they promote the good of our Souls, Bodies and Eſtates, (as I ſhall ſhew you preſently) and as Members of Society, they conſult our Good, in that they promote mutual Good-will, Love, Peace, Unity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus Juſtice preſerving our own as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Rights, makes us eaſie in our Stations, and promotes mutual Confidence in one another, which would naturally produce Peace and Unity, and ſo our Charity to our Brethren gains us an univerſal Love and Reſpect from Men, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Readineſs to relieve our Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, upon Occaſion, in a grateful return. Laſtly, the unviolated Authority of Conſcience diſpoſeth Magiſtrates to <hi>rule well,</hi> and Subjects to be ſtrictly obedient to them; thus Religion in all its Parts is ſo good natur'd that it tends to make Men peaceable and beneficial towards one another, and ſo advance the Intereſt of Mankind in general. And no leſs profitable is it in the</p>
            <p>Second Place to every private Man in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. For it conſults the Good of our Souls, Bodies and Eſtates. As to our Souls,</p>
            <p>In our Obſervance of our Duty towards God, and worſhiping him ſuitably to his Nature, our Underſtandings are directly led to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the nobleſt Truths, our Wills <note place="margin">Pſ. 73. 25, 26, 27.</note> to their embraces of their chiefeſt Good, <hi>and our Affections</hi> are hereby fixed on what they ought to be, <hi>viz. the Things above.</hi> And ſo all the Faculties of the Soul being kept in their due Order, and employed to their proper Ends, our Souls live and act according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152530:21"/> their own Nature, and conſequently muſt needs enjoy great Peace and Tranquility. Becauſe there are no Diſorders of the Paſſions, no Fears of Guilt to interrupt it. And therefore <hi>great peace have they who love thy Law, and nothing ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 165</note> 
               <hi>offend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Practice of the forementioned Duties conſult the good of our Bodies, and that by preſerving them in a perfect ſtate of Health; for what can contribute more thereto, than a chearful temper of Mind, and a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 4. 1 Theſſ. 5. 6. 1 Pet. 4. 7. 1 Cor. 9. 25.</note> uſe of Meat and Drink and Recreations, and theſe things Religion teacheth and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of us.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Practice of Religion may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be ſuppoſed to procure a more than ordinary Bleſſing upon theſe prudent, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Means of Health, from that God <hi>who killeth and maketh alive, who bringeth down to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Grave, and bringeth up.</hi> And he accordingly has promiſed, in the Scriptures, Health and long Life as a Reward to the Practice of Religion; for <hi>for length of Days is in her right hand, and ſhe is a Tree of life to them that lay hold upon her.</hi> Wherefore it was an Advice well becoming the <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 16, 18.</note> the Wiſdom of him that gave it. <hi>My Son for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not my Law, but let thine Heart keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; for length of Days and long Life and Peace ſhall they add unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Practice of the forementioned Duties brings down and entails a Bleſſing upon our Eſtates; and that not only by engaging the Kindneſs of Heaven, to have a more eſpecial eye of Providence towards us, both by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 10</note> us to thoſe Duties which naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote our wordly Intereſt. Thus Juſtice and Honeſty bring Men into Repute, that gives them an Opportunity of enlarging their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of Trade, That their Stocks, and Theſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152530:21"/> their Revenues; and though Fraud and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may ſometimes chance to bring us in a preſent Advantage, yet when it is once detected, we loſe more Reputation, and with it more Cuſtomers, than ever the diſhoneſt Gain can compenſate, ſo that Truth and fair Dealing will bear a Man out, when little and ſharking Tricks will fail him. For as the Wiſe-man obſerves, <hi>he that walketh uprightly walketh ſurely.</hi> And ſo Temperance and Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 9.</note> prevent all unneceſſary and extravagant Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes; whereas they who indulge their ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Appetites, to the Violation of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ruin their Eſtates to rights; if we may believe our own Obſervation, or the the Wiſeman's Word, who tells us, <hi>that he who loves Pleaſure ſhall be a Poor Man, and he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 17.</note> 
               <hi>that loveth Wine and Oyl,</hi> (i. e.) love them to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, <hi>ſhall not be rich.</hi> Laſtly, Induſtry and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in our Callings not only cut off ſome Opportunities of Extravagance, but directly tend to encreaſe our Fortunes; Reaſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience both, confirming this as an undeniable Truth, that <hi>the Hand of the Diligent maketh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 4.</note> 
               <hi>rich.</hi> So that when all is done, 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the beſt Husbandry to be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I would further urge you to the Practice of the forementioned Duties, from the great Aſſiſtances that are given us, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them not only eaſie, but pleaſant to us. For God has recommended them to our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Obſervance, with all the moſt powerful Means and Arguments, to engage our Practice of them; <hi>he has ſhewed thee, O Man what is Good; and what does the Lord require of thee, but to do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Micah 6. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtly, and to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> He has not only propoſed theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to us in the Goſpel, with the Promiſes and Terrors of the <hi>Life that now is, and of that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 8. 1</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152530:22"/> 
               <hi>which is to come,</hi> with the <hi>Examples</hi> of the beſt of Men, eſpecially with that more pregnant one of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> together with all thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 21.</note> Motives ariſing from what he did and ſuffered for us, with thoſe mighty Arguments that may be drawn from his Life, Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Aſcention, and his Return to judge both the Quick and the Dead; with Pleaſure and Peace from the Nature of the Duties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 165</note> and with all the Endearments of Love and Kindneſs from him that enjoins them; he not only urgeth us (I ſay) to our Duty upon theſe many and weighty Conſiderations, and that with all the Importunity poſſible to gain our Practice, but has alſo promiſed the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his <hi>Almighty-Spirit</hi> to make all things <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 12.</note> eaſie and pleaſant to us. So that if we do but ſet our ſelves in good earneſt to the Practice of the forementioned Duties, if we do but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beg the Divine Grace, which, we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, ſhall <hi>be ſufficient for us,</hi> and then apply <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> our own Endeavours in a faithful and diligent uſe of it, 'tis impoſſible that we ſhould fail of Succeſs; for <hi>I can do all things,</hi> ſays the <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note> Apoſtle, <hi>through Chriſt that ſtrengthens me.</hi> And this Omnipotent Aſſiſtance we may have, upon the eaſie terms of putting up a Petition for it; for God has engaged to give <hi>the holy Spirit to them that ask him.</hi> And what more eaſie condition <note place="margin">Luke 11. 13</note> can we deſire than this, that <hi>If we ſeek we ſhall find, if we ask we ſhall receive,</hi> receive too that which, <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 7.</note> though we cannot of our ſelves, will yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power us, through our joint Endeavours, to do our Duty with Pleaſure and Delight, and ſo render us both happy here and hereafter too; for This,</p>
            <p>In the 4th and laſt Place is (or ought to be) a further Inducement to our Practice of all the Duties of Religion, becauſe God has made our Duty the indiſpenſable Condition of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 21. Rom. 8. 13.</note> Happineſs, and (as I ſhewed you in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152530:22"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eginning of this Diſcourſe) the neceſſary Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aration <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14 1 Tim. 4. 8.</note> for it. So that 'tis juſt as neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or us to be Religious, or to do our Duty, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is to go to Heaven, or to keep out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lames of Hell. And this ought to be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deration of great Weight with us, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hatever our Condition be in the other World. Whether a happy or a miſerable one, it muſt <note place="margin">Luke 16. 26 2 Pet. 1. 10.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo for ever; ſo that <hi>we had need give all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to make our calling and Election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having, I hope, by theſe Conſiderations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onvinced you of the Neceſſity of doing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orementioned Duties, my next Work is to tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, that what is thus neceſſary to be done, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne time or other, had beſt be done now out <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 10.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f hand. And indeed unleſs we ſet our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the immediate Practice of theſe Duties, is plain that we are not heartily convinced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Neceſſity of doing them at all. Becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur continuance in our Sins do too manifeſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rove our Good-liking to them; and if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll approve and cheriſh them, we are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good Earneſt reconciled to the Practice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e contrary Duties; becauſe we can neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pprove of two different things, nor act two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifferent ways, at the ſame time. So that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve be the Servants of Sin, (as our Intentions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o continue in it for a while plainly ſhew) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cannot be the Servants of Chriſt:</hi> Either there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore we muſt quit our Sins and our favourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oughts of them immediately upon the Spot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r elſe foregoe our Intentions, to fall to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ractice of Religion ſome Years hence; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or he that is a true Convert, is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to be perfectly convinced of the Miſchiefs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his Sin, and the reaſonableneſs of his Duty; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d therefore immediately ſtrikes in with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt Conviction, which, by being full and clear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>revents him making thoſe little Shifts and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olous Excuſes, which others take ſanctuary in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> excuſe their Delay of this neceſſary Work.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152530:23"/> Though with what little, or rather againſt what great reaſon, may be made appear from the following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis extreamly neceſſary that Men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately betake themſelves to their Duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is (as appears from what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid) of very great Concern and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to them, and what is ſo, we are apt, in other Caſes, to beſtow our firſt and chiefeſt Care upon. Thus we ſee in wordly Affairs, how every prudent Man is, more eſpecially, careful to drive on, what he calls the main Chance, &amp; is at little eaſe till this be ſecured, or at leaſt, is in a fair way of being ſo. Now would but <hi>the Children of Light be as wiſe in their Generation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 33.</note> 
               <hi>as the Children of this World are,</hi> they would be as ſollicitous about the Concerns of their Souls, as theſe Men are, of their Bodies. They would no more delay ſecuring the Life of the one, than theſe men do, of the other, when it lyes at Stake, which if any Man ſhould be ſo fool-hardy as to nelect, and by that Neglect loſe his Life, which his care would have ſaved; he would be deſervedly thought to die like a Fool. And certainly much more would that Chriſtian deſerve the Imputation of Folly, who, when his eternal Intereſt is in Danger, ſhall yet ſuffer it to continue ſo, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert his utmoſt Endeavours for the Security of it, and conſequently embrace the firſt Occaſion to ſecure it in; eſpecially conſidering in the</p>
            <p>Second Place, that the Nature of Religion is ſuch, as requires a great deal at our hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it gives us any Right or Title to that great and neceſſary Reward; without which we are undone for ever; our ſenſual Appeties muſt be ſubdued, the Deeds of the Body mortified, <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 13. Eph. 2. 22, 23, 24. Col. 3. 2.</note> our Deſires reſigned, our Affections weaned from this World, and raiſed to the things above, in ſhort, our Minds muſt be transformed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152530:23"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om Carnal to Spiritual, and this requires more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me and pains than moſt Men think for; let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en but try the Experiment upon one Luſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſee what Pangs and Throes of Mind, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ruglings and Conflicts, what Watchings and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rayers, are neceſſary before they can make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfect conqueſt of that one. And then they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill tell me, that a greater and more early <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, than e're they dream't of, is but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to carry on the great Deſign of Religion which is the Life and Happineſs of their Souls) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith good Succeſs. And therefore Religion as wiſely, as well as kindly, provided us with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rious helps, both to prevent the Trouble of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>forming a bad Life, and to promote an early <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſuccesful progreſs in a Good one, to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpoſe we are, when Children, admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Chriſtian Religion by Baptiſm, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing therein made <hi>Members of Chriſt, Children of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and Inheritours of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngage all the Powers of Heaven on our ſide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> enable us to begin, continue and end our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives, in a conſtant Obſervance of our Duty; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which end, there are Securities given of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur being educated in the Truth; and as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow up, we have the daily Adminiſtration of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Word and Sacrament, the one, to put us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n mind of our Baptiſmal Vow, the other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o give us the Opportunity of renewing it. We have alſo the inward Influences of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine Grace to encourage, and aſſiſt our conſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeavours of proceeding on from one degree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Grace to another in our Chriſtian Courſe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſo we are required <hi>to add to our ſaith Vertue,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 1. 5, 6, 7, 8.—3. 18</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Vertue, Knowledge, to Knowledge, Temperance, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on, and ſo to grow in Grace, and in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtly, <hi>to perfect holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> By <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll which you plainly ſee, that to defer, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut off our Duty for the preſent, with deſign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o betake our ſelves to the practice of it, 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152530:24"/> or 30 Years hence, or at the latter end of our Days, is directly contrary to the Nature and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Religion, and is an open Violation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Breach of our ſacred Vows and Obligations made in our Baptiſm; which is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent, that it is highly ſinful, and will infallibly betray Men into <hi>eternal Damnation</hi> in the other World, if Death ſhould chance to cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them off (as 'tis probable he will) before they have executed their Intentions of conforming to the Duties of Religion; and 'tis yet more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that they may not have (what they ſo much truſt to) the Opportunity of being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious afterwards: As will further appear, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That as this Life is the only Time of Probation, on which our Eternal Happineſs or Miſery depends; ſo it is but a very uncertain Caſt, to have things of ſo great Moment depend upon it, for <hi>What is our Life? it is even a Vapour,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">James 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>that appeareth for a little Time, and then vaniſheth away;</hi> a Vapour, which we can take no Hold of, but, for all we know, may ſlip through our Fingers before to morrow Morning: So that <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 1.</note> the only Time we can be ſure of, is the preſent, and That is ſo ſwift, that whilſt we are think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Job 7. 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> and ſpeaking of It, it is gone, and paſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: And therefore there is no Delaying with Things of ſo ſlippery a Nature, and ſo quick a Motion. 'Tis in vain to think, that Time ſhould leave its natural Property, to ſtop a while, and wait our Leiſure; it were Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as well as Vain, to deſire, that God would alter the Nature of Things, to gratifie our lazy Humour; no, fond Men! Time as it ſtays for no Man, ſo, (whether ye will think fit to enjoy it or not,) will moſt certainly hurry you o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to a long Eternity. And therefore, to make ſuitable Preparation for This, ye had need be as nimble as Time it ſelf, and employ every Minute that is given you to the beſt Advantage;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152530:24"/> whereby ye ſhould beſt comply with the wiſe Deſign of the Donor of it; for how liberal ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver God has been of all his other Bleſſings to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, yet this of Time he has been pleaſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſpenſe in a leſs plentiful manner, chooſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her to give it by Minutes, to ſignifie how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious It is, and that we ſhould be ſparing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrifty of it, diligent to <hi>Redeem</hi> That which is <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 15, 16. 1 Pet. 4. 2. Heb. 3. 13.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt, and careful to improve That which is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, <hi>To Day therefore, whilſt it is called to Day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e exhorted</hi> to the Practice of your Duty, <hi>leſt any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou be hardned through the Deceitfulneſs of Sin:</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Suppoſing that God ſhould be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind to us beyond our Deſerts; though not our Deſires, as to prolong our Days, yet it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſonable to expect, that the Divine Grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould be always at our Beck, and continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ait our Leiſure. This were to deſire, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Grace of God would be more kind and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtant to us, than we are to our ſelves, that whereas we intend to beſtow no more than our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpiring Breath, in calling upon God, we would have his Grace attend us, through the ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tages of our Sins, and court us to our Duty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the very laſt Gaſp. But, <hi>Be not deceived, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oever</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7. Prov. 21. 24, 28.</note> 
               <hi>a Man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap.</hi> What God threatned to the <hi>Old World,</hi> he will moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertainly, make good to all old habitual Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, <hi>viz. That his Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 3. Luke 19. 42.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith Men;</hi> but, <hi>the Things belonging to their Peace, if they will not know them now in this their Day,) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill,</hi> moſt aſſuredly, <hi>be hid from their Eyes.</hi> And his our Bleſſed Saviour has ſignified to us in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arable of the Talents, where he ſays, at the Concluſion of that Parable, <hi>from him that hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 29.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot, ſhall be taken away even That which he ſeemeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have.</hi> It is therefore the moſt ſeaſonable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>holſom Advice, that either the Prophet could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive, or We could take, <hi>viz. Seek ye the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 55. 6. 2 Cor. 6. 2.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hilſt he may be found, call ye upon him whilſt He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> near. For now is the accepted Time, now is the</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152530:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152530:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152530:26"/> 
               <hi>Day of Salvation.</hi> But as for the Time to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 'tis every whit as uncertain, whether we ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fall to the Practice of our Duty hereafter, if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> live, as whether we ſhall live to Hereafter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fall to the Practice of our Duty. For if Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould now withdraw his Grace (as Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their reſolved Contempt of it juſtly provo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him,) they are left in as great an Incapaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of becoming Religious, as if He had withdraw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Lives: <hi>It being as poſſible to repent witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Life, when we are Dead, as without God's Grace wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we are Living,</hi> (as a late Divine has obſerved <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>'s <hi>Chriſt. Life,</hi> Part Firſt.</note> So that here are two Hazards to be run at onc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which, if either fail, (and yet both are out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our Power,) will irrecoverably ruine our ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal Salvation, which is ſtaked upon Them; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe are, that we ſhall certainly live to be Ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and as certainly have the Divine Grace to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come Religious when we are ſo; wherea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (God knows) we may be dead by the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Job 24. 22. Matth. 13. 12. Eph. 2. 1.</note> Hour, and perhaps already are, or at leaſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be, (if we reſolve to delay our Reformation, <hi>dead alſo in Treſpaſſes and Sins.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> If we defer the Practice of our Dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it will grow every Day more difficult than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and ſo That which is now eaſie to be pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed, will not hereafter be done without great deal of Trouble; for all the Time w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indulge our Luſts, we do but the more ſtrengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en them againſt our Selves; for bad Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nations, the longer they are let alone, the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they improve; and vitious Habits, the oft n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they are repeated, grow but the more confir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and inveterate: For, what a mighty Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er there is in a Habit in general, may be ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in almoſt every Concern of Life: How eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and almoſt neceſſarily do Men thoſe Thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereof they have the Habit? inſomuch th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they cannot without trouble act otherwiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they have broken the Habit, either by Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> or a contrary Practice. What then ſhall we thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152530:26"/> of the Habits of Sin, which bend the Sinner to vicious Courſes, not only by Means of their ſtrong and natural Tendency that is in Them, as Habits, but moreover and above receive an additional Strength from the too too willing Inclinations of Men, which ſtrike in with the Habit, and by a wonderful Force hurry the poor Sinner into Wickedneſs, almoſt beyond a natural Poſſibility of a Recovery, eſpecially when ſuch an Habit hath been a long Time ſettled and confirmed in him? For it then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Governing Principle, and is as it were, a Second Nature; ſo that he is almoſt under <note place="margin">Jer. 13. 23.</note> the fatal Neceſſity of continuing in It: And accordingly we read in Scripture of ſome Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who are arrived to that <hi>Perfection in Vice,</hi> that they ſin with a peculiar Glee, <hi>working all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs with Greedineſs;</hi> they commit their Sins with ſuch a vehement Thirſt, that they are ſaid <hi>to drink Iniquity like Water;</hi> and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Job 15. 16.</note> become ſuch perfect Slaves to their Vices, that <hi>They are ſold under Sin, led captive by Satan at</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 14. 2 Tim. 2. 26.</note> 
               <hi>his Will.</hi> Now this is the Effect of thoſe ſinful Habits, which the Delays of a good Life, or (which is all one) the Practice of a bad one, do neceſſarily bring us under. And this is an Effect, which, by cutting off our chief Hopes of being truly Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igious, after a long and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Courſe of Sinning, renders it highly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, nay, even neceſſary <hi>to make haſte, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 60.</note> 
               <hi>delay not to keep God's Commandments;</hi> eſpecially conſidering in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixth</hi> Place, That the longer we defer this great Work, the leſs able ſhall we be <hi>on our Parts</hi> to perform it. For when Sickneſs or Old Age comes (the Seaſons I ſuppoſe, to which Sinners intend to put off the Practice of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uty,) they bring a World of Troubles along with Them; which muſt needs weaken the Powers of our Souls, and indiſpoſe them for that great Work, which we have cut out for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152530:27"/> Them: For does not Experience teſtifie, That every little Indiſpoſition of Body indiſpoſeth our Souls alſo? Do we not find, that Sickneſs many times impairs our Memories, raiſes in us ſuch Heats and Fumes as confound our Senſes, and diſtract our Thoughts, if not rob us wholly of the preſent Uſe of our Underſtandings? And when we can neither remember, perceive, nor underſtand, but are all Agony, Confuſion, and Diſtraction, we are very unfit Perſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a Work, that requires a perfect Memory, a ſound Judgment, and ſteady Reſolution; a perfect Memory to call to mind the many Failings and Miſcarriages of a long and ſinful Life; A ſound Judgment to ſtate the Caſe fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly between God and our own Souls; and ſteady Reſolutions to live and die in Acts of new Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. This is the leaſt we muſt do, and yet it is many times more, than what our Sickneſs will ſuffer us to perform; the Violence of ſome Diſtempers being ſuch as takes away at once, our Reaſon and our Senſes, and with them all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Reforming: But ſuppoſing that through the Bleſſing of God, and an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrength of Nature, we eſcape this dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Enemy to a late Repentance, and arrive to an unrelenting Old Age; yet we can't in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon think This a proper time to begin the <hi>Mortification</hi> of our Luſts, the <hi>Renovation</hi> of our Natures, and <hi>Our growth in Grace.</hi> For is it likely we ſhould <hi>grow</hi> in This, when we have done growing every Way, but in Age and Wickedneſs? Or, is it poſſible to revive our periſhing Souls, when we our ſelves are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins?</hi> Or, can we hope to conquer with feeble Joints and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Knees, thoſe powerful Luſts which have been ſo long victorious over all our braveſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions? Alas! theſe Enemies which have been all our Life long ſtrengthning Themſelves againſt us, are not ſo eaſily maſter'd by us now,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152530:27"/> now that our Strength to reſiſt Them is decayed and gone, ſo that we cannot now reaſonably hope to work any other Mortification upon our Luſts, than what Age has already given Them. This indeed may weaken their Strength in time; but what is that to us? What Old Age of it ſelf doth, is not our Act; nor does it concern us further, than only to ſhew us, with Reproach and Shame, what we ought to have done, <hi>viz.</hi> to have made that Act our own, and have mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified our Luſts our ſelves; for which, we are now beholden to our Old Age: So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Goodneſs we ſhall, or can now exert, we may reaſonably ſuſpect to be more the Effect of our Impotence and Weakneſs, than of a ſound Judgment and a free Choice; and if ſo, we cannot aſſume the Performance of it to our Selves, becauſe, That which is done with hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and diſabled Faculties, with an imperfect Knowledge and Conſent, is not properly our own <hi>Act and Deed;</hi> and yet this is much the caſe of old Folks, who, as ſuch, are diſtemper'd, that is, have all the Faculties of their Souls, the Members of their Bodies; and in ſhort, all their Powers of Action very much worn out, cramp'd, and diſabled. So that to put off the doing our Duty to a Time of Sickneſs, or Old Age, is next Door to not doing it at all; and therefore we muſt not think to put it off <hi>from Day to Day,</hi> but now or never reſolve upon it: For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Now is the moſt proper Seaſon to do our Duty in. For now our Enemies are fewer, and leſs able to offend us, and We more able to defend our Selves againſt Them. Now our ſinful Habits are not ſo ſtrong, nor our Sins ſo numerous as they will be afterwards: And therefore we have now leſs Work than ever we ſhall have upon our Hands; and, what is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Encouragement, our Faculties are now moſt vigorous, moſt fit to engage in this neceſſary Undertaking; and Now too, is the only Time
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152530:28"/> 
               <hi>to ſerve God acceptably.</hi> Now is the proper Seaſon to exerciſe our Graces, to ſhew the Reality and Strength of them; Now, that there are proper <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 3. James 1. 12. Eccleſ. 11. 9.</note> Temptations both to try and improve Them. For, 'tis now in <hi>the Days of our Youth</hi> that the World beſets us with Enchantments, and that our own Bodies turn Tempters to us: 'Tis now that the Gaities of the World are apt to allure us! Tis now that the Unrulineſs of our Blood, and the ill Propenſities of the Fleſh, prompt us to the Breach of thoſe Vows, which we have taken up againſt Them. So that Now is the proper Seaſon for the Exerciſe of Religion. For now, if we can reſiſt theſe unruly Motions, and <hi>keep our Selves unſpotted from the World,</hi> we ſhall <note place="margin">James 1. 27. Prov. 23. 26. Mark 12. 33. Prov. 14. 14. Eccleſ. 12. 1.</note> manifeſtly prove our Faith and Piety to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, which will infallibly recommend it to the Divine Acceptance, and afford no little Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to our Selves. It was therefore an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice well-becoming the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon; Remember now thy Creator in the Days of thy Youth, while the evil Days come not, nor the Year draw nigh, when thou ſhalt ſay, I have no Pleaſure in them.</hi> For in ſuch <hi>a Time of Trouble</hi> as Old Age is, (which the Wiſe Man here deſcribes,) we cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hope, that our Souls, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Preparation, ſhould be duly qualify'd to perform any Service acceptable to Him, <hi>who is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hab. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of purer Eyes than to behold the leaſt Iniquity.</hi> Alas! all the Faculties of our Souls will, long before that Time, be grown Reſtive for want of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and Improvement, and what is worſe, They will be over-run with our Luſts and Vices. And Now to devote the Powers of our Souls to the Service of our God, when weaken'd as much as poſſible by our Luſts, would be <hi>to offer him the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Malach. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Blind, the Lame, and the Sick, for Sacrifice:</hi> And ſhould he accept ſuch an Offering at our Hands, <hi>Offer it now to thy Governour,</hi> ſays God, <hi>and ſee if</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> 
               <hi>he will be pleaſed with Thee or accept thy Perſon?</hi> Much leſs will he, who <hi>is King of Kings and Lord</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152530:28"/> 
               <hi>of Lords.</hi> And indeed, if Sinners would but ſpeak out and tell the Truth, they muſt needs own, that their Religious Exerciſes, like all their other Actions of Life, are at that Time of Day very troubleſom and uneaſie to Them: And would it not be very unreaſonable to expect, that God ſhould delight in thoſe Dregs of our Lives, which we our Selves can take no Pleaſure in? Sinners ſurely muſt have a very mean Opinion both of God and Religion too, to think Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fit enough for the Service of Both, when they are diſabled and unfit for every thing elſe: Though properly ſpeaking, it is no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but (as you have ſeen) only the Effect of Impotence and Weakneſs, that they can then preſent him with; for what Vertue can there be in Men's inſignificant Intentions to begin to be Good, at a time when perhaps they can't (if they would) be actually Bad? This is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in plain Engliſh, to have the Thoughts of ſerving God, when they can ſerve the Devil no longer: And what a ſad Thing is it to live ſo long in Wickedneſs, as at length to be forſaken by It? And then, when our Sins have left us, rather than we them, we will even look out for a better Maſter, and begin to ſerve God, <hi>who never faileth Them that ſeek him:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Amos 5. 4. Pſal. 9. 10.</note> Why ſhould he not <hi>be Gracious unto us now at laſt?</hi> Why may not we find as much Grace and Favour at our laſt Minutes as the <hi>Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 20. 1. Luke 23. 42.</note> did, who came into their <hi>Lord's Vineyard</hi> at the laſt Hour, or as the <hi>Thief upon the Croſs?</hi> who could not have converted Later, nor yet had a more comfortable Promiſe made over to him upon his Converſion, as Late as it was.</p>
            <p>Now as to the former of theſe Inſtances al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in Favour of a late Repentance, namely, That of the <hi>Labourers</hi> going late into the <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> to work; it is by Learned Men thought, that the whole Deſign of that Parable is, only to exhibit or ſet forth to us the Juſtice and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152530:29"/> of God, in tendring the Light and Mercies of the Goſpel to the Gentiles, and rewarding their late Acceptance of them equal with the <hi>Jews,</hi> that were called before us; and ſo it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in the Opinion of ſome, to the Caſe of private Sinners. Though I will (for once) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it does; but withal muſt obſerve, That this gives no Encouragement to any Sinner to defer the Reformation of his Life, or the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Religion to the laſt, no, nor yet to the next Hour; for ſuppoſing the <hi>Eleventh Hour</hi> in the Parable to ſignifie the Laſt of our Lives, and that God did accept and reward Thoſe that converted to Him then; yet it does not appear, that They who were then <hi>Hired into the Vineyard,</hi> or called to Repentance, had rejected more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Invitations to it; but whether Idleneſs, or whatever was the Occaſion of their late Call and Converſion, this is certain, that at what Hour ſoever, whether at the Firſt, Sixth, or Ninth, they were called, they immediately o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Motion, and needed not a ſecond Call, as Men now a-days do, <hi>who ſtop their Ears</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 5.</note> 
               <hi>at the Voice of the Charmers, charming never ſo wiſely;</hi> and ſo <hi>they add to all their Sins this One,</hi> (and that a very great One too,) of Obſtinacy and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigibleneſs, which render their Caſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Labourers, it being far more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely that ſuch ſtubborn Tempers ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wrought unto Repentance and Reformation, eſpecially to that which is ſincere; 'tis far more likely that God, being by their Stubbornneſs provoked, <hi>ſhould give them over to a reprobate Mind.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then as to the other Inſtance of a late Repentance, that of the <hi>Thief on the Croſs.</hi> Here I will ſuppoſe, (becauſe I know Sinners do) that this late Penitent's Life was as theirs is, but one continued Courſe of Wickedneſs, of which he repented not till his laſt Minutes; and that as God did graciouſly pardon him then, ſo may he forgive them alſo, if they do but then repent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152530:29"/> as heartily as he did; yet I hope to ſhew them, that they have no reaſonable Encouragement from this Example, to continue in their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs at Preſent, in hopes of finding Mercy upon their Repentance at Laſt, or at a dying Hour, as will appear if they conſider, That 'tis poſſible, nay probable, that this Thief might never have heard of the Name of Jeſus before, or if he had, it might not have been propoſed to him with ſufficient Motives of Credibility; and if this (as I could ſhew you we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think) was his Caſe, it was more his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs than his Crime, that He converted and believed no ſooner. Yet when He was converted and did believe, He lived up ſtrictly to the Terms of the Goſpel, that little while he had to live: For he here on the Croſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his Sin; begs Pardon for it; <hi>accepts the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 23. 40, 41, 42.</note> 
               <hi>Puniſhment of his Iniquity;</hi> commiſerates that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Condition that was but juſt now his own; He pityeth the Innocent; <hi>confeſſeth with his Mouth the Lord Jeſus; believeth in his Heart.</hi> And theſe were the only Things he had then at liberty; and therefore he could do nothing more, to ſhew himſelf a Faithful Diſciple of <hi>the Crucified Jeſus.</hi> He owns him <hi>King,</hi> even when there was the leaſt Appearance of his being ſuch, and fixeth his Hope as firmly in Him as if <hi>all Power in Heaven and Earth had been already given to him.</hi> He ſhews an extraordinary Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty both in Opinion and Action, in Opinion in judging our Saviour <hi>to have done nothing amiſs.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">—41.</note> His Charity in Action, in endeavouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim his Fellow, by reproving him for his Sin, <note place="margin">—40, 41.</note> which he does (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> obſerves) before he asks any Thing for himſelf. Now what is it that Sinners do like this, in all their Life, to give them <hi>Hope in their Death?</hi> Can they, who <hi>from their Baptiſm have lived the reſt of their Time to the Luſts of Men, and not to the Will of God,</hi> pretend to an immediate Acceptance of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152530:30"/> Terms of the Goſpel? Can He, who lives in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Contradiction to the Divine Commands, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending only to conform to Them when he has no further Strength to break Them, can ſuch a one ſay, that he ſtrictly adheres to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace? Or can He, who by his long continued Habits of ſinning, has weakned all the Powers of his Soul, and ſtrengthned nothing but his Luſts; can He (I ſay) in reaſon ſuppoſe, that he has not made himſelf <hi>twofold more a Child of Hell</hi> than <hi>a Saint of Heaven?</hi> Can he be ſaid to be <hi>ſtrong in Faith,</hi> who, notwithſtanding our Saviour's Reſurrection, the Conſent of the beſt and wiſeſt Men, the wonderful Conqueſt made by the Goſpel over the Hearts and Lives of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, (ſhewing It to be <hi>the Power of God unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note>) who, (I ſay) notwithſtanding all this clear Evidence of Belief, can yet ſhew themſelves the only obdurate Wretches, and diſown their Saviour, now that <hi>He is in his Kingdom?</hi> And what reaſonable Grounds of Hope can ſuch Men have, who are ſo far from being <hi>pure from their Sins,</hi> that they daily <hi>ſtrengthen Themſelves in their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Wickedneſs?</hi> And as to their Charity, Is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that they ſhould have any true <hi>Love</hi> for their <hi>Brother,</hi> who have little or none for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? How can they commiſerate anothers unhappy Condition, when they do not ſo much as pity their own? Or, How can they pretend to any Love for God, whom they intend to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front <note place="margin">John 14, 15.—15. 14.</note> all their Life-time, and at their Death <hi>to ſeek him,</hi> more out of Dread and Fear of him, than an ardent Affection towards him? How ſhall they delight in the <hi>Preſence</hi> of him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, whom they could not endure to think of here? or ſuppoſing They could hereafter reliſh any Pleaſure in the ſweet Society of Him, who now is <hi>leaſt in all their Thoughts,</hi> yet what Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation have they laid for ſuch <hi>a Converſation in Heaven?</hi> Alas! their Graces are all to ſeek, and yet without theſe, it is impoſſible that they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152530:30"/> ſhould ever be <hi>meet to be Partakers of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the Saints in Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further, The Circumſtances and Manner of this <hi>Penitent's</hi> Death were ſuch as never any Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were before Him, nor ever can be again, unleſs our Bleſſed Lord ſhould <hi>once more become obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs;</hi> and one of thoſe, (who deſires to make this <hi>Penitent's</hi> Caſe his own,) had never heard of the <hi>Name</hi> of Chriſt, till he chance to ſuffer with him, and then, by inſtantly believing in him, ſhould once again procure an extraordinary ſhare of Mercy from our <hi>merciful High Prieſt,</hi> who was pleaſed to give the firſt Proof of his being ſuch to this Bleſſed <hi>Penitent,</hi> when he ſaid to Him, <hi>To day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Now ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lucky juncture as this can never occur again, (becauſe Chriſt was not <hi>to offer himſelf often;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 25.</note>) but ſuppoſing it could, yet this ſurpaſſing the ſtanding Meaſures, and Methods of God's Grace, cannot be fairly drawn into Example, no more than Acts of Mercy and Oblivion from a Prince upon extraordinary Occaſions, can encourage his rebellious Subjects always to expect the like Favour. The only Ground whereon they can found any reaſonable Hopes of Pardon, is their immediate return to their Duty and Obedience; and this muſt be every Man's great Care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <note place="margin">Lev. 26. 41, 42. Luke 15. 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Job 8. 5, 6. 1 Joh. 3. 3. Prov. 10. 9. Prov. 14. 32. Pſal. 23. 4. Prov. 12. 2. Rom. 2. 7.</note> Endeavour in reſpect to God, in order to procure Pardon and Acceptance of him. His early Application to all the Duties of Religion, and his final Perſeverance in Them, is the only hope of Mercy. This is certainly moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, moſt ſafe to himſelf, and will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him the greateſt Comfort when he ſhall ſtand in the greateſt need of it, I mean, at a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hour: For a well-ſpent Life infallibly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures to us (as ye have ſeen) the Favour of God here, <hi>which is better than Life,</hi> and his Glory and Happineſs hereafter, which is the Life and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our Souls.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152530:31"/>
               <head>A ſhort Prayer to be ſaid upon our firſt Kneeling down at Church.</head>
               <p>PArdon, O Lord, all my Sins, which make me unworthy to come into thy Preſence, or <hi>to tread thy Courts:</hi> Quicken my Devotions to Thee. <hi>Open my Heart to attend unto Things that ſhall be ſpoken,</hi> and grant that we may all <hi>come together for the better, and not for the worſe,</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Prayer to be ſaid at Church immediately after Prayers, or Sermon.</head>
               <p>BE pleaſed, O Lord, to accept this my Duty and Service, and to pardon the Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it. Grant it may ſo tend to my Spiritual Improvement, as may enable me to ſerve Thee better for the future; that <hi>going from Strength to Strength,</hi> I may at length <hi>appear before thee in Zion,</hi> even in thy heavenly Kingdom, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Divine Grace to aſſiſt us in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the various Duties mentioned in the foregoing Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>MOST glorious Lord God, the great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Heaven and Earth, and our moſt merciful Father in Chriſt Jeſus. Thou art the Fountain of all Perfections, and the very Life and Happineſs of all our Souls; we therefore thine unworthy Cereatures <hi>ſinful Duſt and Aſhes,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our Selves before Thee, to praiſe thee for the infinite Perfections of thy Nature, and to beg of Thee the neceſſary Supplies of thy Grace and Holy Spirit, <hi>that we may give thee the Honour due unto thy Name,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip thee</hi> ſuitably to thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with <hi>an holy and a ſpiritual Worſhip.</hi> Thou art of purer Eyes than to behold the leaſt Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and therefore how ſhall ſuch polluted Wretches as we are, dare to approach thy dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Majeſty, who by our Sins and Follies have made our ſelves ſo unlike to thee, <hi>who art righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152530:31"/> 
                  <hi>in all thy Ways and holy in all thy Works?</hi> How then ſhall we preſume to come into thy holy Preſence, who are defiled in our very Natures, having nothing but Vanity and Blindneſs in our Minds, Perverſneſs in our Wills, both ſpiritual and carnal Iniquity in our Affections and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and what is worſe, have defiled our Selves yet much more, by our many actual and habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sins againſt thee, ſo that we are altogether unworthy to approach thy Preſence, or expect thy Favour, and yet have ſo great need of both, that without them, we are loſt for ever: O therefore <hi>caſt us not away from thy Preſence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from us!</hi> but out of Pity to thy defective and diſeaſed Creatures, <hi>receive us graciouſly,</hi> and <hi>heal our Souls, though we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt Thee.</hi> Reſcue us from the Power and Bondage of our Luſts by the greater Power of thy Grace. Renew and purifie our corrupted Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Create in us a clean Heart, O God, and renew a right Spirit within us.</hi> Teach us a perfect Denial of all our Sins, and eſtabliſh us in a ſtedfaſt Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all thy Laws. To which End, enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our Minds to form clear and true Notions of Thee, and open our Hearts to attend upon all the Means that may help us to diſcharge our various Obligations to Thee. Inſpire our Souls with thy heavenly Graces. Strengthen our Faith, confirm our Hope, encreaſe our Love, quicken our Fear, eſtabliſh our Truſt, inſpire us with Patience, Conſtancy and Sincerity. Enflame our Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and envigorate our Endeavours, in a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſcharge of our Duty to Thee. Give us thy Grace alſo to aſſiſt us in the Peformance of <hi>our Duty to our Neighbour,</hi> that we may ever remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and conſtantly obſerve thy great and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law, <hi>to love him as our ſelves,</hi> and to this End grant, That we may never defraud Him of his Right, but give him his due in all the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards us wherein he ſtands. Diſpoſe us therefore, good Lord, chearfully <hi>to obey Them that</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152530:32"/> 
                  <hi>have the Rule over us,</hi> whether in Church or State; and bleſs them in an happy Government of us; <hi>that under them we may lead qulet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Lives in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> Bleſs all Sorts of Parents and Maſters; grant that they may faithfully diſcharge the various Duties of their Stations, and their reſpective Inferiours may, in a grateful Return thereof, ever Love, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Obey them. Grant to all Men, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, the <hi>Spirit to think, and do all ſuch Things as be rightful,</hi> ever adhering to that equitable Rule, <hi>the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing as they would be dealt by.</hi> And grant us, O thou Fountain of Mercy and Love, a univerſal Charity towards all Men, even to our Enemies, that we may be ever ready both to forgive and alſo to provide, <hi>that they which are in need and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity have Righte</hi> in a ſuitable Relief of their vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wants; and becauſe our Prayers to Thee, <hi>from whom every good and perfect Gift cometh,</hi> are oft the beſt and only Helps we can afford them, therefore do thou, O Lord, abundantly for them, more than we can ask or think. Suit thy Mercies according to their various Neceſſities; ſanctifie their Afflictions to them, and when thou ſeeſt it beſt for them, give them a happy Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of all their Troubles. And Laſtly, O Lord, we come unto thee for a Bleſſing upon our Selves, who, as we are here Living Inſtances of thine Almighty Power and Goodneſs, ſo be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make us the happy Inſtruments of thy Praiſe and Glory; to which Purpoſe enable us to ſubject all the Faculties of our Souls, and the Powers of our Bodies to thy bleſſed Will, which is the Law and Perfection of our reaſonable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Direct our Underſtandings to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe glorious Manifeſtations which thou haſt been pleaſed to give us of thy ſelf. Clear up our Apprehenſions both of the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of thy Nature, and the Excellency of thoſe Perfections. Direct our Wills to the Choice and Imitation of ſuch thy Perfections as are imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152530:32"/> by us. Teach us the Wiſdom to proportion our Affections of Things, according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Value of them, that having a leſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for this World, we may fear thee more, and love thee better: Give us a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght Underſtanding of our Selves, of our own Inſufficiency, and of our entire Dependance upon thee, that ſo <hi>we may not think more highly of our ſelves than we ought to think.</hi> Teach us a chearful Submiſſion to thine all-wiſe Diſpenſations, and <hi>in whatever State we are, therewith to be content.</hi> Endue us with a calm and gentle Temper of Soul, ſuch as may invite thy Bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> to come, and <hi>take up his Abode with us,</hi> that through his Bleſſed Operations, we may bring forth the Fruits of the Spirit <hi>in Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs,</hi> and <hi>Temperance.</hi> Subdue our bodily Appetites to the Laws of our Reaſon, and the End of their Creation, ever remembring that our <hi>Bodies are the Temples of the Holy Spirit;</hi> and that <hi>he who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth the Temple of God, him thou haſt threatned to deſtroy.</hi> Out of an holy Fear and Dread of this, and all other thy reaſonable Threats, grant that we may be ever careful to <hi>keep under our Bodies, and cleanſe our Selves from all Filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit,</hi> that ſo we may (as we are in Duty bound) <hi>glorifie thee in our Body, and in our Spirit, which are Thine;</hi> and we not only beg thy Grace to aſſiſt us in, but thy heavenly Wiſdom, to ſhew us the reaſonableneſs and neceſſity of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of theſe Duties, <hi>that we may make haſte and delay not to keep thy Commandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND as we deſire this Morning to enter into <note place="margin">For the Morning.</note> the World upon our lawful Occaſions, with this holy Frame and Diſpoſition of Soul, ſo grant, that we may never loſe it, either through Surprize, or wilful Neglect, but guide us ſafely by thy Grace, through all the Dangers and Temptations of this, and all other Days of our Life; that, <hi>eſcaping the Corruption that is in the World through Luſt,</hi> we may live and die thy faithful and obedient Servants.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:152530:33"/>
               <p> AND now, O Lord, that we are going to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <note place="margin">For the Evening.</note> our ſelves, <hi>keep us from all Dangers and Adverſities that may happen to our Bodies,</hi> and <hi>from all evil Thoughts</hi> and Dreams, <hi>which may aſſault and hurt our Souls,</hi> that we may riſe in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a freſh ſenſe upon our Minds of thy Mercies to us, and a full Conviction of the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of expreſſing our Thankfulneſs, not only with our Lips, but in the conſtant Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our Lives, ſpending that Strength which thou haſt given us, to thy Honour and Service; to whom we owe our utmoſt Praiſes, for all thy free and undeſerved Mercies: Therefore</p>
               <p>We not only pray unto thee, but deſire to bleſs thee for all thy Benefits from time to time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us, for thy Creation of us out of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for thy Preſervation of us ever ſince we had a Being, for all the Accommodations of this Life, and the plentiful Proviſion thou haſt made for our Happineſs in the other; for all that thy Son our dear Redeemer, has done and ſuffer'd for us, for his wonderful Incarnation and Birth, for his exemplary Life, his meritorious Death and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for his glorious Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, and for his ſending the Holy Ghoſt to comfort us; for all thy Saints and Servants departed this Life in thy true Faith and Fear, beſeeching thee to give us Grace ſo to follow their good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that with them we may be Partakers of thy heavenly Kingdom: Theſe Prayers and Praiſes, with whatever elſe thou in thine infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſeeſt moſt neceſſary and expedient for us, we humbly offer up in the Name and for the Sake of thy Son, our bleſſed Saviour and Redeemer, who has commanded us, when we pray, to ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer may be uſed by one Perſon, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changing the Words <hi>We, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and <hi>Our,</hi> into <hi>I, Me,</hi> and <hi>My,</hi> and ſaying inſtead of Creatures <hi>Creature,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:152530:33"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
